<?xml version = "1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="XSL/Tanach.xsl.xml"?>
<!-- Copyright C.V.Kimball 2010 -->
<Tanach>
<!-- 
     The following is a simplified version of the About page. 
     and is intended to be read only by search engines.
     Actual operation is through the XSLT transformation file,
     XSL/Tanach.xsl.xml, specified above. 
-->
<h1>Unicode/XML Leningrad Codex</h1>
The Hebrew bible, the Tanach, has been transcribed from the electronic text of
the Leningrad Codex maintained by the J. Alan Groves Center for Advanced 
Biblical Research to a modern Unicode and XML-based format. The Coding page 
describes the transcription process. The license of use is very generous.
<p/>
Text can be rapidly accessed by providing a citation, i.e. Deut 26:5-9, in a 
text field or by clicking on a succession of links. Text can be displayed in a
variety of formats and font sizes. Hebrew text may be highlighted, copied, and
pasted into Unicode compatible applications. Books of the Torah have an option
to display source markings of the Documentary Hypothesis (DH). Files include a
standard Text Encoding Initiative header describing the provenance of the text.
<p/>
<ul>
<li>The Hebrew text is freely available  in 5 formats: text, HTML, XML, ODT 
(Open Document Text), or PDF (Portable Document Format). Complete books in each
of these formats with selectable content (Accents, Vowels, Consonants, 
Morphology) are available. Zipped archives of complete books in different 
formats and contents are also available.  The text files are an official 
repository of the Groves Center for the Westminster Leningrad Codex in Unicode.
</li><p/>
<li>Standalone servers are available for text (TextServer), HTML (HTMLServer), 
XML (XMLServer), and ODT (ODTServer) formats. 
</li><p/>
<li>The site can be operated <i>without an internet connection</i>.
</li><p/>
<li>An RSS feed of random verses provides a learning challenge.
</li><p/>
<li>Text-dependent links to external sites, such as translations, may be 
created. 
</li><p/> 
</ul>
<p/>
Notices about the site are published on the <b>b-hebrew</b> mailing list at 
<b><tt>http://lists.ibiblio.org/mailman/listinfo/b-hebrew</tt></b>.  The 
subject line of the notices contains the phrase "Unicode/XML Westminster 
Leningrad Codex".
<p/>
Transcriber: Christopher V. Kimball, West Redding, CT, USA
<p/>
</Tanach>
