<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bible>
   <section id="THE WRITINGS">
      <book id="LAMENTATIONS">
         
            <hebrew-title>איכה</hebrew-title>
            <book-title>LAMENTATIONS</book-title>
            
         
         <chapter-number>1</chapter-number>
         <verse-letter>א</verse-letter> 
         <small-caps>How</small-caps>
         <small-caps> doth</small-caps> the city sit solitary,  <paragraph-break/> That was full of people!   <paragraph-break/>How is she become as a widow!   <paragraph-break/>She that was great among the nations,   <paragraph-break/>And princess among the provinces,   <paragraph-break/>How is she become tributary!  <verse-letter>ב</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>She weepeth sore in the night,   <paragraph-break/>And her tears are on her cheeks;   <paragraph-break/>She hath none to comfort her   <paragraph-break/>Among all her lovers;   <paragraph-break/>All her friends have dealt treacherously with her,   <paragraph-break/>They are become her enemies.  <verse-letter>ג</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>Judah is gone into exile because of affliction,   <paragraph-break/>And because of great servitude;   <paragraph-break/>She dwelleth among the nations,   <paragraph-break/>She findeth no rest;   <paragraph-break/>All her pursuers overtook her   <paragraph-break/>Within the straits.  <verse-letter>ד</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>The ways of Zion do mourn,   <paragraph-break/>Because none come to the solemn assembly;   <paragraph-break/>All her gates are desolate,   <paragraph-break/>Her priests sigh;   <paragraph-break/>Her virgins are afflicted,   <paragraph-break/>And she herself is in bitterness.  <verse-letter>ה</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Her adversaries are become the head,   <paragraph-break/>Her enemies are at ease;   <paragraph-break/>For the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> hath afflicted her   <paragraph-break/>For the multitude of her transgressions;  
          <paragraph-break/>Her young children are gone into captivity   <paragraph-break/>Before the adversary.  <verse-letter>ו</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>And gone is from the daughter of Zion   <paragraph-break/>All her splendour;   <paragraph-break/>Her princes are become like harts   <paragraph-break/>That find no pasture,   <paragraph-break/>And they are gone without strength   <paragraph-break/>Before the pursuer.   <verse-letter>ז</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>Jerusalem remembereth   <paragraph-break/>In the days of her affliction and of her anguish   <paragraph-break/>All her treasures that she had   <paragraph-break/>From the days of old;   <paragraph-break/>Now that her people fall by the hand of the adversary,   <paragraph-break/>And none doth help her,   <paragraph-break/>The adversaries have seen her,   <paragraph-break/>They have mocked at her desolations.  <verse-letter>ח</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>Jerusalem hath grievously sinned,   <paragraph-break/>Therefore she is become as one unclean;   <paragraph-break/>All that honoured her despise her,   <paragraph-break/>Because they have seen her nakedness;   <paragraph-break/>She herself also sigheth,   <paragraph-break/>And turneth backward.  <verse-letter>ט</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>Her filthiness was in her skirts,   <paragraph-break/>She was not mindful of her end;   <paragraph-break/>Therefore is she come down wonderfully,   <paragraph-break/>She hath no comforter.  
         
         
            
         
          <paragraph-break/>’Behold, O <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>, my affliction,   <paragraph-break/>For the enemy hath magnified himself.’  <verse-letter>י</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>The adversary hath spread out his hand   <paragraph-break/>Upon all her treasures;   <paragraph-break/>For she hath seen that the heathen   <paragraph-break/>Are entered into her sanctuary,   <paragraph-break/>Concerning whom Thou didst command   <paragraph-break/>That they should not enter into Thy congregation.  <verse-letter>כ</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>All her people sigh,   <paragraph-break/>They seek bread;   <paragraph-break/>They have given their pleasant things for food   <paragraph-break/>To refresh the soul.  <paragraph-break/>‘See, O <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>, and behold,   <paragraph-break/>How abject I am become.’   <verse-letter>ל</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>‘Let it not come unto you, all ye that pass by!   <paragraph-break/>Behold, and see   <paragraph-break/>If there be any pain like unto my pain,   <paragraph-break/>Which is done unto me,   <paragraph-break/>Wherewith the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> hath afflicted me   <paragraph-break/>In the day of His fierce anger.  <verse-letter>מ</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>From on high hath He sent fire   <paragraph-break/>Into my bones, and it prevaileth against them;   <paragraph-break/>He hath spread a net for my feet,   <paragraph-break/>He hath turned me back;   <paragraph-break/>He hath made me desolate   <paragraph-break/>And faint all the day.  <verse-letter>נ</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>The yoke of my transgressions is impressed by His hand;  <paragraph-break/>They are knit together,  
         <paragraph-break/>They are come up upon my neck;  <paragraph-break/>He hath made my strength to fail;  <paragraph-break/>The Lord hath delivered me into their hands,  <paragraph-break/>Against whom I am not able to stand.  <verse-letter>ס</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>The Lord hath set at nought  <paragraph-break/>All my mighty men in the midst of me;  <paragraph-break/>He hath called a solemn assembly against me  <paragraph-break/>To crush my young men;  <paragraph-break/>The Lord hath trodden as in a winepress  <paragraph-break/>The virgin the daughter of Judah.’  <verse-letter>ע</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>‘For these things I weep;  <paragraph-break/>Mine eye, mine eye runneth down with water;  <paragraph-break/>Because the comforter is far from me,  <paragraph-break/>Even he that should refresh my soul;  <paragraph-break/>My children are desolate,  <paragraph-break/>Because the enemy hath prevailed.’  <verse-letter>פ</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>Zion spreadeth forth her hands;   <paragraph-break/>There is none to comfort her;   <paragraph-break/>The <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> hath commanded concerning Jacob,   <paragraph-break/>That they that are round about him should be his adversaries;   <paragraph-break/>Jerusalem is among them   <paragraph-break/>As one unclean.   <verse-letter>צ</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>‘The <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> is righteous;  <paragraph-break/>For I have rebelled against His word;  <paragraph-break/>Hear, I pray you, all ye peoples,   <paragraph-break/>And behold my pain:   <paragraph-break/>My virgins and my young men   <paragraph-break/>Are gone into captivity.  
         
         
            
         
         <verse-letter>ק</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>I called for my lovers,  <paragraph-break/>But they deceived me;  <paragraph-break/>My priests and mine elders  <paragraph-break/>Perished in the city,  <paragraph-break/>While they sought them food  <paragraph-break/>To refresh their souls.  <verse-letter>ר</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>Behold, O <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>, for I am in distress,  <paragraph-break/>Mine inwards burn;  <paragraph-break/>My heart is turned within me,  <paragraph-break/>For I have grievously rebelled.  <paragraph-break/>Abroad the sword bereaveth,  <paragraph-break/>At home there is the like of death.  <verse-letter>ש</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>They have heard that I sigh,  <paragraph-break/>There is none to comfort me;  <paragraph-break/>All mine enemies have heard of my trouble, and are glad,  <paragraph-break/>For Thou hast done it;  <paragraph-break/>Thou wilt bring the day that Thou hast proclaimed,  <paragraph-break/>And they shall be like unto me.  <verse-letter>ת</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>Let all their wickedness come before Thee;  <paragraph-break/>And do unto them,  <paragraph-break/>As Thou hast done unto me  <paragraph-break/>For all my transgressions;  <paragraph-break/>For my sighs are many  <paragraph-break/>And my heart is faint.’  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
         <verse-letter>א</verse-letter>How hath the Lord covered  with a cloud  <paragraph-break/>The daughter of Zion in His anger!  <paragraph-break/>He hath cast down from heaven unto the earth  <paragraph-break/>The beauty of Israel,  <paragraph-break/>And hath not remembered His footstool  <paragraph-break/>In the day of His anger.  
         <verse-letter>ב</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>The Lord hath swallowed up unsparingly  <paragraph-break/>All the habitations of Jacob;  <paragraph-break/>He hath thrown down in His wrath  <paragraph-break/>The strongholds of the daughter of Judah;  <paragraph-break/>He hath brought them down to the ground;  <paragraph-break/>He hath profaned the kingdom and the princes thereof.  <verse-letter>ג</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>He hath cut off in fierce anger  <paragraph-break/>All the horn of Israel;  <paragraph-break/>He hath drawn back His right hand  <paragraph-break/>From before the enemy;  <paragraph-break/>And He hath burned in Jacob like a flaming fire,  <paragraph-break/>Which devoureth round about.  <verse-letter>ד</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>He hath bent His bow like an enemy,  <paragraph-break/>Standing with His right hand as an adversary,  <paragraph-break/>And hath slain all that were pleasant to the eye;  <paragraph-break/>In the tent of the daughter of Zion  <paragraph-break/>He hath poured out His fury like fire.  <verse-letter>ה</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>The Lord is become as an enemy,  <paragraph-break/>He hath swallowed up Israel;  <paragraph-break/>He hath swallowed up all her palaces,  <paragraph-break/>He hath destroyed his strongholds;  <paragraph-break/>And He hath multiplied in the daughter of Judah  <paragraph-break/>Mourning and moaning.  <verse-letter>ו</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>And He hath stripped His tabernacle, as if it were a garden,  <paragraph-break/>He hath destroyed His place of assembly;  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>The <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> hath caused to be forgotten in Zion  <paragraph-break/>Appointed season and sabbath,  <paragraph-break/>And hath rejected in the indignation of His anger  <paragraph-break/>The king and the priest.  <verse-letter>ז</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>The Lord hath cast off His altar,  <paragraph-break/>He hath abhorred His sanctuary,  <paragraph-break/>He hath given up into the hand of the enemy  <paragraph-break/>The walls of her palaces;  <paragraph-break/>They have made a noise in the house of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>,  <paragraph-break/>As in the day of a solemn assembly.  <verse-letter>ח</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>The <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> hath purposed to destroy  <paragraph-break/>The wall of the daughter of Zion;  <paragraph-break/>He hath stretched out the line,  <paragraph-break/>He hath not withdrawn  <paragraph-break/>His hand from destroying;  <paragraph-break/>But He hath made the rampart and wall to mourn,  <paragraph-break/>They languish together.  <verse-letter>ט</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>Her gates are sunk into the ground;  <paragraph-break/>He hath destroyed and broken her bars;  <paragraph-break/>Her king and her princes are among the nations,  <paragraph-break/>Instruction is no more;  <paragraph-break/>Yea, her prophets find  <paragraph-break/>No vision from the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>.  <verse-letter>י</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>They sit upon the ground, and keep silence,  <paragraph-break/>The elders of the daughter of Zion;  <paragraph-break/>They have cast up dust upon their heads,  <paragraph-break/>They have girded themselves with sackcloth;  <paragraph-break/>The virgins of Jerusalem hang down  <paragraph-break/>Their heads to the ground.  
         <verse-letter>כ</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>Mine eyes do fail with tears,  <paragraph-break/>Mine inwards burn,  <paragraph-break/>My liver is poured upon the earth,  <paragraph-break/>For the breach of the daughter of my people;  <paragraph-break/>Because the young children and the sucklings swoon  <paragraph-break/>In the broad places of the city.  <verse-letter>ל</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>They say to their mothers:  <paragraph-break/>‘Where is corn and wine?’  <paragraph-break/>When they swoon as the wounded  <paragraph-break/>In the broad places of the city,  <paragraph-break/>When their soul is poured out  <paragraph-break/>Into their mothers’bosom.  <verse-letter>מ</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>What shall I take to witness for thee?  <paragraph-break/>What shall I liken to thee,  <paragraph-break/>O daughter of Jerusalem?  <paragraph-break/>What shall I equal to thee, that I may comfort thee,  <paragraph-break/>O virgin daughter of Zion?  <paragraph-break/>For thy breach is great like the sea;  <paragraph-break/>Who can heal thee?  <verse-letter>נ</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>Thy prophets have seen visions for thee  <paragraph-break/>Of vanity and delusion;  <paragraph-break/>And they have not uncovered thine iniquity,  <paragraph-break/>To bring back thy captivity;  <paragraph-break/>But have prophesied for thee burdens  <paragraph-break/>Of vanity and seduction.  <verse-letter>ס</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>All that pass by clap  <paragraph-break/>Their hands at thee;  <paragraph-break/>They hiss and wag their head  <paragraph-break/>At the daughter of Jerusalem:  <paragraph-break/>‘Is this the city that men called  <paragraph-break/>The perfection of beauty,  <paragraph-break/>The joy of the whole earth?’  
         
         
            
         
         <verse-letter>פ</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>All thine enemies have opened  <paragraph-break/>Their mouth wide against thee;  <paragraph-break/>They hiss and gnash the teeth;  <paragraph-break/>They say: ‘We have swallowed her up;  <paragraph-break/>Certainly this is the day that we looked for;  <paragraph-break/>We have found, we have seen it.’  <verse-letter>ע</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>The <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> hath done that which He devised;  <paragraph-break/>He hath performed His word  <paragraph-break/>That He commanded in the days of old;  <paragraph-break/>He hath thrown down unsparingly;  <paragraph-break/>And He hath caused the enemy to rejoice over thee,  <paragraph-break/>He hath exalted the horn of thine adversaries.   <verse-letter>צ</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>Their heart cried unto the Lord:  <paragraph-break/>‘O wall of the daughter of Zion,  <paragraph-break/>Let tears run down like a river  <paragraph-break/>Day and night;  <paragraph-break/>Give thyself no respite;  <paragraph-break/>Let not the apple of thine eye cease.  <verse-letter>ק</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>Arise, cry out in the night,  <paragraph-break/>At the beginning of the watches;  <paragraph-break/>Pour out thy heart like water  <paragraph-break/>Before the face of the Lord;  <paragraph-break/>Lift up thy hands toward Him  <paragraph-break/>For the life of thy young children,  <paragraph-break/>That faint for hunger  <paragraph-break/>At the head of every street.’  <verse-letter>ר</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>‘See, O <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>, and consider,  <paragraph-break/>To whom Thou hast done thus!  <paragraph-break/>Shall the women eat their fruit,  <paragraph-break/>The children that are dandled in the hands?  
         <paragraph-break/>Shall the priest and the prophet be slain  <paragraph-break/>In the sanctuary of the Lord?  <verse-letter>ש</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>The youth and the old man lie  <paragraph-break/>On the ground in the streets;  <paragraph-break/>My virgins and my young men  <paragraph-break/>Are fallen by the sword;  <paragraph-break/>Thou hast slain them in the day of Thine anger;  <paragraph-break/>Thou hast slaughtered unsparingly.  <verse-letter>ת</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>Thou hast called, as in the day of a solemn assembly,  <paragraph-break/>My terrors on every side,  <paragraph-break/>And there was none in the day of the <small-caps>Lord’s</small-caps> anger  <paragraph-break/>That escaped or remained;  <paragraph-break/>Those that I have dandled and brought up  <paragraph-break/>Hath mine enemy consumed.’   <verse-letter>א</verse-letter>
         <chapter-number>3</chapter-number>I am the man that hath seen  affliction  <paragraph-break/>By the rod of His wrath.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>He hath led me and caused me to walk in darkness and not in light.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>Surely against me He turneth His hand again and again all the day.  <verse-letter>ב</verse-letter>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>My flesh and my skin hath He worn out;  <paragraph-break/>He hath broken my bones.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>He hath builded against me, and compassed me  <paragraph-break/>With gall and travail.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>He hath made me to dwell in dark places,  <paragraph-break/>As those that have been long dead.  <verse-letter>ג</verse-letter>
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>He hath hedged me about, that I cannot go forth;  <paragraph-break/>He hath made my chain heavy.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>Yea, when I cry and call for help, He shutteth out my prayer.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>He hath enclosed my ways with hewn stone,  <paragraph-break/>He hath made my paths crooked.  <verse-letter>ד</verse-letter> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>He is unto me as a bear lying in wait,  <paragraph-break/>As a lion in secret places.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>He hath turned aside my ways, and pulled me in pieces;  <paragraph-break/>He hath made me desolate.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>He hath bent His bow, and set me  <paragraph-break/>As a mark for the arrow.  <verse-letter>ה</verse-letter>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>He hath caused the arrows of His quiver  <paragraph-break/>To enter into my reins.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>I am become a derision to all my people,  <paragraph-break/>And their song all the day.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>He hath filled me with bitterness,  <paragraph-break/>He hath sated me with wormwood.  <verse-letter>ו</verse-letter> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>He hath also broken my teeth with gravel stones,  <paragraph-break/>He hath made me to wallow in ashes.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>And my soul is removed far off from peace,  <paragraph-break/>I forgot prosperity.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>And I said: ‘My strength is perished,  <paragraph-break/>And mine expectation from the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>.’  <verse-letter>ז</verse-letter> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>Remember mine affliction and mine anguish,  <paragraph-break/>The wormwood and the gall.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>My soul hath them still in remembrance,  <paragraph-break/>And is bowed down within me.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>This I recall to my mind, Therefore have I hope.  <verse-letter>ח</verse-letter> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>Surely the <small-caps>Lord’s</small-caps> mercies are not consumed,  <paragraph-break/>Surely His compassions fail not.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>They are new every morning;  <paragraph-break/>Great is Thy faithfulness.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>‘The <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> is my portion’, saith my soul;  <paragraph-break/>‘Therefore will I hope in Him.’  <verse-letter>ט</verse-letter> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>The <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> is good unto them that wait for Him,  <paragraph-break/>To the soul that seeketh Him.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>It is good that a man should quietly wait  <paragraph-break/>For the salvation of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>It is good for a man that he bear   <paragraph-break/>The yoke in his youth.  <verse-letter>י</verse-letter> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>Let him sit alone and keep silence,  <paragraph-break/>Because He hath laid it upon him.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>29</verse-number>Let him put his mouth in the dust,  <paragraph-break/>If so be there may be hope.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>30</verse-number>Let him give his cheek to him that smiteth him  <paragraph-break/>Let him be filled full with reproach.  <verse-letter>כ</verse-letter> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>31</verse-number>For the Lord will not cast off  <paragraph-break/>For ever.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>32</verse-number>For though He cause grief, yet will He have compassion  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>According to the multitude of His mercies.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>33</verse-number>For He doth not afflict willingly,  <paragraph-break/>Nor grieve the children of men.  <verse-letter>ל</verse-letter> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>34</verse-number>To crush under foot  <paragraph-break/>All the prisoners of the earth,  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>35</verse-number>To turn aside the right of a man  <paragraph-break/>Before the face of the Most High,  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>36</verse-number>To subvert a man in his cause,  <paragraph-break/>The Lord approveth not.  <verse-letter>מ</verse-letter> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>37</verse-number>Who is he that saith, and it cometh to pass,  <paragraph-break/>When the Lord commandeth it not?  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>38</verse-number>Out of the mouth of the Most High proceedeth not  <paragraph-break/>Evil and good?  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>39</verse-number>Wherefore doth a living man complain,  <paragraph-break/>A strong man because of his sins?  <verse-letter>נ</verse-letter> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>40</verse-number>Let us search and try our ways,  <paragraph-break/>And return to the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>41</verse-number>Let us lift up our heart with our hands  <paragraph-break/>Unto God in the heavens.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>42</verse-number>We have transgressed and have rebelled;  <paragraph-break/>Thou hast not pardoned.  <verse-letter>ס</verse-letter> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>43</verse-number>Thou hast covered with anger and pursued us;  <paragraph-break/>Thou hast slain unsparingly.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>44</verse-number>Thou hast covered Thyself with a cloud,  <paragraph-break/>So that no prayer can pass through.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>45</verse-number>Thou hast made us as the offscouring and refuse  
         <paragraph-break/>In the midst of the peoples.  <verse-letter>פ</verse-letter> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>46</verse-number>All our enemies have opened their mouth  <paragraph-break/>Wide against us.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>47</verse-number>Terror and the pit are come upon us,  <paragraph-break/>Desolation and destruction.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>48</verse-number>Mine eye runneth down with rivers of water,  <paragraph-break/>For the breach of the daughter of my people.  <verse-letter>ע</verse-letter> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>49</verse-number>Mine eye is poured out, and ceaseth not,  <paragraph-break/>Without any intermission,  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>50</verse-number>Till the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> look forth,  <paragraph-break/>And behold from heaven.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>51</verse-number>Mine eye affected my soul,  <paragraph-break/>Because of all the daughters of my city.  <verse-letter>צ</verse-letter> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>52</verse-number>They have chased me sore like a bird,  <paragraph-break/>That are mine enemies without cause.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>53</verse-number>They have cut off my life in the dungeon,  <paragraph-break/>And have cast stones upon me.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>54</verse-number>Waters flowed over my head;  <paragraph-break/>I said: ‘I am cut off.’  <verse-letter>ק</verse-letter> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>55</verse-number>I called upon Thy name, O <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>,  <paragraph-break/>Out of the lowest dungeon.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>56</verse-number>Thou heardest my voice; hide not  <paragraph-break/>Thine ear at my sighing, at my cry.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>57</verse-number>Thou drewest near in the day that I called upon Thee;  <paragraph-break/>Thou saidst: ‘Fear not.’  
         
         
            
         
         <verse-letter>ר</verse-letter> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>58</verse-number>O Lord, Thou hast pleaded the causes of my soul;  <paragraph-break/>Thou hast redeemed my life.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>59</verse-number>O <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>, Thou hast seen my wrong;  <paragraph-break/>Judge Thou my cause.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>60</verse-number>Thou hast seen all their vengeance  <paragraph-break/>And all their devices against me.  <verse-letter>ש</verse-letter> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>61</verse-number>Thou hast heard their taunt, O <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>,  <paragraph-break/>And all their devices against me;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>62</verse-number>The lips of those that rose up against me,  <paragraph-break/>And their muttering against me all the day.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>63</verse-number>Behold Thou their sitting down, and their rising up;  <paragraph-break/>I am their song.  <verse-letter>ת</verse-letter> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>64</verse-number>Thou wilt render unto them a recompense, O <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>,  <paragraph-break/>According to the work of their hands.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>65</verse-number>Thou wilt give them hardness of heart,  <paragraph-break/>Thy curse unto them.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>66</verse-number>Thou wilt pursue them in anger, and destroy them  <paragraph-break/>From under the heavens of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>4</chapter-number>
         <verse-letter>א</verse-letter> How is the gold become dim!   <paragraph-break/>How is the most fine gold      changed!  <paragraph-break/>The hallowed stones are poured out  <paragraph-break/>At the head of every street.  <verse-letter>ב</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>The precious sons of Zion,  <paragraph-break/>Comparable to fine gold,  
         <paragraph-break/>How are they esteemed as earthen pitchers,  <paragraph-break/>The work of the hands of the potter!  <verse-letter>ג</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>Even the jackals draw out the breast,  <paragraph-break/>They give suck to their young ones;  <paragraph-break/>The daughter of my people is become cruel,  <paragraph-break/>Like the ostriches in the wilderness.  <verse-letter>ד</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>The tongue of the sucking child cleaveth  <paragraph-break/>To the roof of his mouth for thirst;  <paragraph-break/>The young children ask bread,  <paragraph-break/>And none breaketh it unto them.  <verse-letter>ה</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>They that did feed on dainties  <paragraph-break/>Are desolate in the streets;  <paragraph-break/>They that were brought up in scarlet   <paragraph-break/>Embrace dunghills.  <verse-letter>ו</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>For the iniquity of the daughter of my people is greater  <paragraph-break/>Than the sin of Sodom,  <paragraph-break/>That was overthrown as in a moment,  <paragraph-break/>And no hands fell upon her.  <verse-letter>ז</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>Her princes were purer than snow,  <paragraph-break/>They were whiter than milk,  <paragraph-break/>They were more ruddy in body than rubies,  <paragraph-break/>Their polishing was as of sapphire;  <verse-letter>ח</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>Their visage is blacker than a coal;  <paragraph-break/>They are not known in the streets;  <paragraph-break/>Their skin is shrivelled upon their bones;  <paragraph-break/>It is withered, it is become like a stick.  <verse-letter>ט</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>They that are slain with the sword are better  <paragraph-break/>Than they that are slain with hunger;  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>For these pine away, stricken through,  <paragraph-break/>For want of the fruits of the field.  <verse-letter>י</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>The hands of women full of compassion  <paragraph-break/>Have sodden their own children;  <paragraph-break/>They were their food  <paragraph-break/>In the destruction of the daughter of my people.   <verse-letter>כ</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>The <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> hath accomplished His fury,  <paragraph-break/>He hath poured out His fierce anger;  <paragraph-break/>And He hath kindled a fire in Zion,  <paragraph-break/>Which hath devoured the foundations thereof.  <verse-letter>ל</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>The kings of the earth believed not,  <paragraph-break/>Neither all the inhabitants of the world,  <paragraph-break/>That the adversary and the enemy would enter  <paragraph-break/>Into the gates of Jerusalem.  <verse-letter>מ</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>It is because of the sins of her prophets,  <paragraph-break/>And the iniquities of her priests,  <paragraph-break/>That have shed the blood of the just  <paragraph-break/>In the midst of her.  <verse-letter>נ</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>They wander as blind men in the streets,  <paragraph-break/>They are polluted with blood,  <paragraph-break/>So that men cannot  <paragraph-break/>Touch their garments.  <verse-letter>ס</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>‘Depart ye! unclean! ’ men cried unto them,  <paragraph-break/>‘Depart, depart, touch not’;  <paragraph-break/>Yea, they fled away and wandered;  <paragraph-break/>Men said among the nations:  <paragraph-break/>‘They shall no more sojourn here.’  
         <verse-letter>פ</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>The anger of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> hath divided them;  <paragraph-break/>He will no more regard them;  <paragraph-break/>They respected not the persons of the priests,  <paragraph-break/>They were not gracious unto the elders.   <verse-letter>ע</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>As for us, our eyes do yet fail  <paragraph-break/>For our vain help;  <paragraph-break/>In our watching we have watched  <paragraph-break/>For a nation that could not save.  <verse-letter>צ</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>They hunt our steps,  <paragraph-break/>That we cannot go in our broad places;  <paragraph-break/>Our end is near, our days are fulfilled;  <paragraph-break/>For our end is come.  <verse-letter>ק</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>Our pursuers were swifter  <paragraph-break/>Than the eagles of the heaven;  <paragraph-break/>They chased us upon the mountains,  <paragraph-break/>They lay in wait for us in the wilderness.  <verse-letter>ר</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>The breath of our nostrils, the anointed of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>,  <paragraph-break/>Was taken in their pits;  <paragraph-break/>Of whom we said: ‘Under his shadow  <paragraph-break/>We shall live among the nations.’  <verse-letter>ש</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>Rejoice and be glad, O daughter of Edom,  <paragraph-break/>That dwellest in the land of Uz:  <paragraph-break/>The cup shall pass over unto thee also;  <paragraph-break/>Thou shalt be drunken, and shalt make thyself naked.  <verse-letter>ת</verse-letter>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>The punishment of thine iniquity is accomplished, O daughter of Zion,  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>He will no more carry thee away into captivity;  <paragraph-break/>He will punish thine iniquity, O daughter of Edom,  <paragraph-break/>He will uncover thy sins.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>5</chapter-number>Remember, O <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>, what is come  upon us;  <paragraph-break/>Behold, and see our reproach.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>Our inheritance is turned unto strangers,  <paragraph-break/>Our houses unto aliens.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>We are become orphans and fatherless,  <paragraph-break/>Our mothers are as widows.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>We have drunk our water for money;  <paragraph-break/>Our wood cometh to us for price.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>To our very necks we are pursued;  <paragraph-break/>We labour, and have no rest.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>We have given the hand to Egypt,  <paragraph-break/>And to Assyria, to have bread enough;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>Our fathers have sinned, and are not;  <paragraph-break/>And we have borne their iniquities.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>Servants rule over us;  <paragraph-break/>There is none to deliver us out of their hand.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>We get our bread with the peril of our lives  <paragraph-break/>Because of the sword of the wilderness.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>Our skin is hot like an oven  <paragraph-break/>Because of the burning heat of famine.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>They have ravished the women in Zion,  <paragraph-break/>The maidens in the cities of Judah.  
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>Princes are hanged up by their hand;  <paragraph-break/>The faces of elders are not honoured.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>The young men have borne the mill,  <paragraph-break/>And the children have stumbled under the wood.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>The elders have ceased from the gate,  <paragraph-break/>The young men from their music.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>The joy of our heart is ceased;  <paragraph-break/>Our dance is turned into mourning.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>The crown is fallen from our head;  <paragraph-break/>Woe unto us! for we have sinned.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>For this our heart is faint,  <paragraph-break/>For these things our eyes are dim;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>For the mountain of Zion, which is desolate,  <paragraph-break/>The foxes walk upon it.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>Thou, O <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>, art enthroned for ever,  <paragraph-break/>Thy throne is from generation to generation.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>Wherefore dost Thou forget us for ever,  <paragraph-break/>And forsake us so long time?  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>Turn Thou us unto Thee, O <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>, and we shall be turned;  <paragraph-break/>Renew our days as of old.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>Thou canst not have utterly rejected us,  <paragraph-break/>And be exceeding wroth against us!  <paragraph-break/>
         <extra-text>Turn us unto Thee, O Lord, and we shall be turned; Renew our days as of old.</extra-text>
         
      </book>
   </section>
</bible>