<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bible>
   <section id="THE WRITINGS">
      <book id="PROVERBS">
         
            
            <hebrew-title>משלי</hebrew-title>
            <book-title>PROVERBS</book-title>
            
            <paragraph-break/>
            
         
         <chapter-number>1</chapter-number>The proverbs of Solomon the son of David, king of Israel;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>To know wisdom and instruction;  <paragraph-break/>To comprehend the words of understanding;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>To receive the discipline of wisdom,  <paragraph-break/>Justice, and right, and equity;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>To give prudence to the simple,  <paragraph-break/>To the young man knowledge and discretion;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>That the wise man may hear, and increase in learning,  <paragraph-break/>And the man of understanding may attain unto wise counsels;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>To understand a proverb, and a figure;  <paragraph-break/>The words of the wise, and their dark sayings.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>The fear of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> is the beginning of knowledge;  <paragraph-break/>But the foolish despise wisdom and discipline.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>Hear, my son, the instruction of thy father,  <paragraph-break/>And forsake not the teaching of thy mother;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>For they shall be a chaplet of grace unto thy head,  <paragraph-break/>And chains about thy neck.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>My son, if sinners entice thee,  
         <paragraph-break/>Consent thou not.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>If they say: ‘Come with us,  <paragraph-break/>Let us lie in wait for blood,  <paragraph-break/>Let us lurk for the innocent without cause;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>Let us swallow them up alive as the grave,  <paragraph-break/>And whole, as those that go down into the pit;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>We shall find all precious substance,  <paragraph-break/>We shall fill our houses with spoil;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>Cast in thy lot among us;  <paragraph-break/>Let us all have one purse’— <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>My son, walk not thou in the way with them,  <paragraph-break/>Restrain thy foot from their path;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>For their feet run to evil,  <paragraph-break/>A nd they make haste to shed blood.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>For in vain the net is spread  <paragraph-break/>In the eyes of any bird;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>And these lie in wait for their own blood,  <paragraph-break/>They lurk for their own lives.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>So are the ways of every one that is greedy of gain;  <paragraph-break/>It taketh away the life of the owners thereof.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>Wisdom crieth aloud in the streets,  <paragraph-break/>She uttereth her voice in the broad places;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>She calleth at the head of the noisy streets,  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>At the entrances of the gates, in the city, she uttereth her words:  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>‘How long, ye thoughtless, will ye love thoughtlessness?  <paragraph-break/>And how long will scorners delight them in scorning,  <paragraph-break/>And fools hate knowledge? <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>Turn you at my reproof;  <paragraph-break/>Behold, I will pour out my spirit unto you,  <paragraph-break/>I will make known my words unto you.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>Because I have called, and ye refused,  <paragraph-break/>I have stretched out my hand, and no man attended,  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>But ye have set at nought all my counsel,  <paragraph-break/>And would none of my reproof;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>I also, in your calamity, will laugh,  <paragraph-break/>I will mock when your dread cometh;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>When your dread cometh as a storm,  <paragraph-break/>And your calamity cometh on as a whirlwind;  <paragraph-break/>When trouble and distress come upon you.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>Then will they call me, but I will not answer,  <paragraph-break/>They will seek me earnestly, but they shall not find me.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>29</verse-number>For that they hated knowledge,  <paragraph-break/>And did not choose the fear of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>30</verse-number>They would none of my counsel,  <paragraph-break/>They despised all my reproof.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>31</verse-number>Therefore shall they eat of the fruit of their own way,  
         <paragraph-break/>And be filled with their own devices.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>32</verse-number>For the waywardness of the thoughtless shall slay them,  <paragraph-break/>And the confidence of fools shall destroy them.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>33</verse-number>But whoso hearkeneth unto me shall dwell securely,  <paragraph-break/>And shall be quiet without fear of evil.’  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>2</chapter-number>My son, if thou wilt receive my  words,  <paragraph-break/>And lay up my commandments with thee;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>So that thou make thine ear attend unto wisdom,  <paragraph-break/>And thy heart incline to discernment;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>Yea, if thou call for understanding,  <paragraph-break/>And lift up thy voice for discernment;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>If thou seek her as silver,  <paragraph-break/>And search for her as for hid treasures;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Then shalt thou understand the fear of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>,  <paragraph-break/>And find the knowledge of God.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>For the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> giveth wisdom,  <paragraph-break/>Out of His mouth cometh knowledge and discernment;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>He layeth up sound wisdom for the upright,  <paragraph-break/>He is a shield to them that walk in integrity;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>That He may guard the paths of justice,  <paragraph-break/>And preserve the way of His godly ones.  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>Then shalt thou understand righteousness and justice,  <paragraph-break/>And equity, yea, every good path.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>For wisdom shall enter into thy heart,  <paragraph-break/>And knowledge shall be pleasant unto thy soul;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>Discretion shall watch over thee,  <paragraph-break/>Discernment shall guard thee;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>To deliver thee from the way of evil,  <paragraph-break/>From the men that speak froward things;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>Who leave the paths of uprightness,  <paragraph-break/>To walk in the ways of darkness;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>Who rejoice to do evil,  <paragraph-break/>And delight in the frowardness of evil;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>Who are crooked in their ways,  <paragraph-break/>And perverse in their paths;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>To deliver thee from the strange woman,  <paragraph-break/>Even from the alien woman that maketh smooth her words;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>That forsaketh the lord of her youth,  <paragraph-break/>And forgetteth the covenant of her God.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>For her house sinketh down unto death,  <paragraph-break/>And her paths unto the shades;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>None that go unto her return,  <paragraph-break/>Neither do they attain unto the paths of life;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>That thou mayest walk in the way of good men,  <paragraph-break/>And keep the paths of the righteous.  
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>For the upright shall dwell in the land,  <paragraph-break/>And the whole-hearted shall remain in it.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>But the wicked shall be cut off from the land,  <paragraph-break/>And the faithless shall be plucked up out of it.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>3</chapter-number>My son, forget not my teaching;  But let thy heart keep my  commandments;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>For length of days, and years of life,  <paragraph-break/>And peace, will they add to thee.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>Let not kindness and truth forsake thee;  <paragraph-break/>Bind them about thy neck, write them upon the table of thy heart;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>So shalt thou find grace and good favour  <paragraph-break/>In the sight of God and man.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Trust in the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> with all thy heart,  <paragraph-break/>And lean not upon thine own understanding.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>In all thy ways acknowledge Him,  <paragraph-break/>And He will direct thy paths.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>Be not wise in thine own eyes;  <paragraph-break/>Fear the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>, and depart from evil;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>It shall be health to thy navel,  <paragraph-break/>And marrow to thy bones.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>Honour the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> with thy substance,  <paragraph-break/>And with the first-fruits of all thine increase;  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>So shall thy barns be filled with plenty,  <paragraph-break/>And thy vats shall overflow with new wine.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>My son, despise not the chastening of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>,  <paragraph-break/>Neither spurn thou His correction;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>For whom the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> loveth He correcteth,  <paragraph-break/>Even as a father the son in whom he delighteth.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>Happy is the man that findeth wisdom,  <paragraph-break/>And the man that obtaineth understanding.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>For the merchandise of it is better than the merchandise of silver,  <paragraph-break/>And the gain thereof than fine gold.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>She is more precious than rubies;  <paragraph-break/>And all the things thou canst desire are not to be compared unto her.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>Length of days is in her right hand;  <paragraph-break/>In her left hand are riches and honour.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>Her ways are ways of pleasantness,  <paragraph-break/>And all her paths are peace.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>She is a tree of life to them that lay hold upon her,  <paragraph-break/>And happy is every one that holdest her fast.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>The <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> by wisdom founded the earth;  <paragraph-break/>By understanding He established the heavens.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>By His knowledge the depths were broken up,  
         <paragraph-break/>And the skies drop down the dew.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>My son, let not them depart from thine eyes;  <paragraph-break/>Keep sound wisdom and discretion;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>So shall they be life unto thy soul,  <paragraph-break/>And grace to thy neck.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>Then shalt thou walk in thy way securely,  <paragraph-break/>And thou shalt not dash thy foot.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>When thou liest down, thou shalt not be afraid;  <paragraph-break/>Yea, thou shalt lie down, and thy sleep shall be sweet.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>Be not afraid of sudden terror,  <paragraph-break/>Neither of the destruction of the wicked, when it cometh;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>For the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> will be thy confidence,  <paragraph-break/>And will keep thy foot from being caught.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>Withhold not good from him to whom it is due,  <paragraph-break/>When it is in the power of thy hand to do it.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>Say not unto thy neighbour: ‘Go, and come again,  <paragraph-break/>And to-morrow I will give’; when thou hast it by thee.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>29</verse-number>Devise not evil against thy neighbour,  <paragraph-break/>Seeing he dwelleth securely by thee.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>30</verse-number>Strive not with a man without cause,  <paragraph-break/>If he have done thee no harm.  <paragraph-break/>
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>31</verse-number>Envy thou not the man of violence,  <paragraph-break/>And choose none of his ways.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>32</verse-number>For the perverse is an abomination to the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>;  <paragraph-break/>But His counsel is with the upright.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>33</verse-number>The curse of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> is in the house of the wicked;  <paragraph-break/>But He blesseth the habitation of the righteous.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>34</verse-number>If it concerneth the scorners, He scorneth them,  <paragraph-break/>But unto the humble He giveth grace.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>35</verse-number>The wise shall inherit honour;  <paragraph-break/>But as for the fools, they carry away shame.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>4</chapter-number>Hear, ye children, the instruction  of a father,  <paragraph-break/>And attend to know understanding.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>For I give you good doctrine;  <paragraph-break/>Forsake ye not my teaching.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>For I was a son unto my father,  <paragraph-break/>Tender and an only one in the sight of my mother.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>And he taught me, and said unto me:  <paragraph-break/>‘Let thy heart hold fast my words,  <paragraph-break/>Keep my commandments, and live;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Get wisdom, get understanding;  <paragraph-break/>Forget not, neither decline from the words of my mouth;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Forsake her not, and she will preserve thee;  <paragraph-break/>Love her, and she will keep thee.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>The beginning of wisdom is: Get wisdom;  
         <paragraph-break/>Yea, with all thy getting get understanding.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>Extol her, and she will exalt thee;  <paragraph-break/>She will bring thee to honour, when thou dost embrace her.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>She will give to thy head a chaplet of grace;  <paragraph-break/>A crown of glory will she bestow on thee.’  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>Hear, O my son, and receive my sayings;  <paragraph-break/>And the years of thy life shall be many.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>I have taught thee in the way of wisdom;  <paragraph-break/>I have led thee in paths of uprightness.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>When thou goest, thy step shall not be straitened;  <paragraph-break/>And if thou runnest, thou shalt not stumble.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>Take fast hold of instruction, let her not go;  <paragraph-break/>Keep her, for she is thy life.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>Enter not into the path of the wicked,  <paragraph-break/>And walk not in the way of evil men.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>Avoid it, pass not by it;  <paragraph-break/>Turn from it, and pass on.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>For they sleep not, except they have done evil;  <paragraph-break/>And their sleep is taken away, unless they cause some to fall.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>For they eat the bread of wickedness,  <paragraph-break/>And drink the wine of violence.  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>But the path of the righteous is as the light of dawn,  <paragraph-break/>That shineth more and more unto the perfect day.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>The way of the wicked is as darkness;  <paragraph-break/>They know not at what they stumble.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>My son, attend to my words;  <paragraph-break/>Incline thine ear unto my sayings.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>Let them not depart from thine eyes;  <paragraph-break/>Keep them in the midst of thy heart.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>For they are life unto those that find them,  <paragraph-break/>And health to all their flesh.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>Above all that thou guardest keep thy heart;  <paragraph-break/>For out of it are the issues of life.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>Put away from thee a froward mouth,  <paragraph-break/>And perverse lips put far from thee.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>Let thine eyes look right on,  <paragraph-break/>And let thine eyelids look straight before thee.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>Make plain the path of thy feet,  <paragraph-break/>And let all thy ways be established.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>Turn not to the right hand nor to the left;  <paragraph-break/>Remove thy foot from evil.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>5</chapter-number>My son, attend unto my wisdom;  Incline thine ear to my  understanding;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>That thou mayest preserve discretion,  <paragraph-break/>And that thy lips may keep knowledge.  
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>For the lips of a strange woman drop honey,  <paragraph-break/>And her mouth is smoother than oil;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>But her end is bitter as wormwood,  <paragraph-break/>Sharp as a two-edged sword.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Her feet go down to death;  <paragraph-break/>Her steps take hold on the nether-world;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Lest she should walk the even path of life,  <paragraph-break/>Her ways wander, but she knoweth it not.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>Now therefore, O ye children, hearken unto me,  <paragraph-break/>And depart not from the words of my mouth.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>Remove thy way far from her,  <paragraph-break/>And come not nigh the door of her house;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>Lest thou give thy vigour unto others,  <paragraph-break/>And thy years unto the cruel;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>Lest strangers be filled with thy strength,  <paragraph-break/>And thy labours be in the house of an alien;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>And thou moan, when thine end cometh,  <paragraph-break/>When thy flesh and thy body are consumed,  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>And say: ‘How have I hated instruction,  <paragraph-break/>And my heart despised reproof;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>Neither have I hearkened to the voice of my teachers,  <paragraph-break/>Nor inclined mine ear to them that instructed me!  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>I was well nigh in all evil  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>In the midst of the congregation and assembly.’  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>Drink waters out of thine own cistern,  <paragraph-break/>And running waters out of thine own well.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>Let thy springs be dispersed abroad,  <paragraph-break/>And courses of water in the streets.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>Let them be only thine own,  <paragraph-break/>And not strangers’with thee.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>Let thy fountain be blessed;  <paragraph-break/>And have joy of the wife of thy youth.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>A lovely hind and a graceful doe,  <paragraph-break/>Let her breasts satisfy thee at all times;  <paragraph-break/>With her love be thou ravished always.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>Why then wilt thou, my son, be ravished with a strange woman,  <paragraph-break/>And embrace the bosom of an alien?  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>For the ways of man are before the eyes of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>,  <paragraph-break/>And He maketh even all his paths.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>His own iniquities shall ensnare the wicked,  <paragraph-break/>And he shall be holden with the cords of his sin.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>He shall die for lack of instruction;  <paragraph-break/>And in the greatness of his folly he shall reel.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>6</chapter-number>My son, if thou art become surety  for thy neighbour,  <paragraph-break/>If thou hast struck thy hands for a stranger—
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>Thou art snared by the words of thy mouth,  <paragraph-break/>Thou art caught by the words of thy mouth—<paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>Do this now, my son, and deliver thyself,  <paragraph-break/>Seeing thou art come into the hand of thy neighbour;  <paragraph-break/>Go, humble thyself, and urge thy neighbour.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>Give not sleep to thine eyes, <paragraph-break/> nor slumber to thine eyelids.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Deliver thyself as a gazelle from the hand [of the hunter],  <paragraph-break/>And as a bird from the hand of the fowler.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Go to the ant, thou sluggard;  <paragraph-break/>Consider her ways, and be wise;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>Which having no chief,  <paragraph-break/>Overseer, or ruler,  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>Provideth her bread in the summer,  <paragraph-break/>And gatherest her food in the harvest.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>How long wilt thou sleep, O sluggard?  <paragraph-break/>When wilt thou arise out of thy sleep?  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>‘Yet a little sleep, a little slumber,  <paragraph-break/>A little folding of the hands to sleep’— <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>So shall thy poverty come as a runner,  <paragraph-break/>And thy want as an armed man.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>A base person, a man of iniquity,  <paragraph-break/>Is he that walketh with a froward mouth;  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>That winketh with his eyes, that scrapeth with his feet,  <paragraph-break/>That pointeth with his fingers;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>Frowardness is in his heart, he deviseth evil continually;  <paragraph-break/>He soweth discord.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>Therefore shall his calamity come suddenly;  <paragraph-break/>On a sudden shall he be broken, and that without remedy.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>There are six things which the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> hateth,  <paragraph-break/>Yea, seven which are an abomination unto Him:  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>Haughty eyes, a lying tongue,  <paragraph-break/>And hands that shed innocent blood;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>A heart that deviseth wicked thoughts,  <paragraph-break/>Feet that are swift in running to evil;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>A false witness that breatheth out lies,  <paragraph-break/>And he that soweth discord among brethren.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>My son, keep the commandment of thy father,  <paragraph-break/>And forsake not the teaching of thy mother;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>Bind them continually upon thy heart,  <paragraph-break/>Tie them about thy neck.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>When thou walkest, it shall lead thee,  <paragraph-break/>When thou liest down, it shall watch over thee;  <paragraph-break/>And when thou awakest, it shall talk with thee.  
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>For the commandment is a lamp, and the teaching is light,  <paragraph-break/>And reproofs of instruction are the way of life;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>To keep thee from the evil woman,  <paragraph-break/>From the smoothness of the alien tongue.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>Lust not after her beauty in thy heart;  <paragraph-break/>Neither let her captivate thee with her eyelids.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>For on account of a harlot a man is brought to a loaf of bread,  <paragraph-break/>But the adulteress hunteth for the precious life.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>Can a man take fire in his bosom,  <paragraph-break/>And his clothes not be burned?  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>Or can one walk upon hot coals,  <paragraph-break/>And his feet not be scorched?  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>29</verse-number>So he that goeth in to his neighbour’s wife;  <paragraph-break/>Whosoever toucheth her shall not go unpunished.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>30</verse-number>Men do not despise a thief, if he steal  <paragraph-break/>To satisfy his soul when he is hungry;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>31</verse-number>But if he be found, he must restore sevenfold,  <paragraph-break/>He must give all the substance of his house.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>32</verse-number>He that committeth adultery with a woman lacketh understanding;  <paragraph-break/>He doeth it that would destroy his own soul.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>33</verse-number>Wounds and dishonour shall he get,  <paragraph-break/>And his reproach shall not be wiped away.  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>34</verse-number>For jealousy is the rage of a man,  <paragraph-break/>And he will not spare in the day of vengeance.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>35</verse-number>He will not regard any ransom;  <paragraph-break/>Neither will he rest content, though thou givest many gifts.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>7</chapter-number>My son, keep my words,  <paragraph-break/>And lay up my commandments  with thee.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>Keep my commandments and live,  <paragraph-break/>And my teaching as the apple of thine eye.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>Bind them upon thy fingers,  <paragraph-break/>Write them upon the table of thy heart.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>Say unto wisdom: ‘Thou art my sister’,  <paragraph-break/>And call understanding thy kinswoman;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>That they may keep thee from the strange woman,  <paragraph-break/>From the alien woman that maketh smooth her words.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>For at the window of my house  <paragraph-break/>I looked forth through my lattice;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>And I beheld among the thoughtless ones,  <paragraph-break/>I discerned among the youths,  <paragraph-break/>A young man void of understanding,  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>Passing through the street near her corner,  <paragraph-break/>And he went the way to her house;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>In the twilight, in the evening of the day,  <paragraph-break/>In the blackness of night and the darkness.  
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>And, behold, there met him a woman  <paragraph-break/>With the attire of a harlot, and wily of heart.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>She is riotous and rebellious,  <paragraph-break/>Her feet abide not in her house;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>Now she is in the streets, now in the broad places,  <paragraph-break/>And lieth in wait at every corner.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>So she caught him, and kissed him,  <paragraph-break/>And with an impudent face she said unto him:  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>‘Sacrifices of peace-offerings were due from me;  <paragraph-break/>This day have I paid my vows.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>Therefore came I forth to meet thee,  <paragraph-break/>To seek thy face, and I have found thee.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>I have decked my couch with coverlets,  <paragraph-break/>With striped cloths of the yarn of Egypt.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>I have perfumed my bed  <paragraph-break/>With myrrh, aloes, and cinnamon.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>Come, let us take our fill of love until the morning;  <paragraph-break/>Let us solace ourselves with loves.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>For my husband is not at home,  <paragraph-break/>He is gone a long journey;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>He hath taken the bag of money with him;  <paragraph-break/>He will come home at the full moon.’  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>With her much fair speech she causeth him to yield,  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>With the blandishment of her lips she enticeth him away.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>He goeth after her straightway,  <paragraph-break/>As an ox that goeth to the slaughter,  <paragraph-break/>Or as one in fetters to the correction of the fool;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>Till an arrow strike through his liver;  <paragraph-break/>As a bird hasteneth to the snare—  <paragraph-break/>And knoweth not that it is at the cost of his life.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>Now therefore, O ye children, hearken unto me,  <paragraph-break/>And attend to the words of my mouth.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>Let not thy heart decline to her ways,  <paragraph-break/>Go not astray in her paths.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>For she hath cast down many wounded;  <paragraph-break/>Yea, a mighty host are all her slain.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>Her house is the way to the nether-world,  <paragraph-break/>Going down to the chambers of death.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>8</chapter-number>Doth not wisdom call,  <paragraph-break/>And understanding put forth her   voice?  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>In the top of high places by the way,  <paragraph-break/>Where the paths meet, she standeth;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>Beside the gates, at the entry of the city,  <paragraph-break/>At the coming in at the doors, she crieth aloud:  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>‘Unto you, O men, I call,  <paragraph-break/>And my voice is to the sons of men.  
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>O ye thoughtless, understand prudence,  <paragraph-break/>And, ye fools, be ye of an understanding heart.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Hear, for I will speak excellent things,  <paragraph-break/>And the opening of my lips shall be right things.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>For my mouth shall utter truth,  <paragraph-break/>And wickedness is an abomination to my lips.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>All the words of my mouth are in righteousness,  <paragraph-break/>There is nothing perverse or crooked in them.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>They are all plain to him that understandeth,  <paragraph-break/>And right to them that find knowledge.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>Receive my instruction, and not silver,  <paragraph-break/>And knowledge rather than choice gold.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>For wisdom is better than rubies,  <paragraph-break/>And all things desirable are not to be compared unto her.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>I wisdom dwell with prudence,  <paragraph-break/>And find out knowledge of devices.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>The fear of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> is to hate evil;  <paragraph-break/>Pride, and arrogancy, and the evil way,  <paragraph-break/>And the froward mouth, do I hate.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>Counsel is mine, and sound wisdom;  <paragraph-break/>I am understanding, power is mine.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>By me kings reign,  <paragraph-break/>And princes decree justice.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>By me princes rule,  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>And nobles, even all the judges of the earth.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>I love them that love me,  <paragraph-break/>And those that seek me earnestly shall find me.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>Riches and honour are with me;  <paragraph-break/>Yea, enduring riches and righteousness.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>My fruit is better than gold, yea, than fine gold;  <paragraph-break/>And my produce than choice silver.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>I walk in the way of righteousness,  <paragraph-break/>In the midst of the paths of justice;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>That I may cause those that love me to inherit substance,  <paragraph-break/>And that I may fill their treasuries.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>The <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> made me as the beginning of His way,  <paragraph-break/>The first of His works of old.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>I was set up from everlasting, from the beginning,  <paragraph-break/>Or ever the earth was.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>When there were no depths, I was brought forth;  <paragraph-break/>When there were no fountains abounding with water.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>Before the mountains were settled,  <paragraph-break/>Before the hills was I brought forth;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>While as yet He had not made the earth, nor the fields,  <paragraph-break/>Nor the beginning of the dust of the world.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>When He established the heavens, I was there;  <paragraph-break/>When He set a circle upon the face of the deep,  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>When He made firm the skies above,  
         <paragraph-break/>When the fountains of the deep showed their might,  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>29</verse-number>When He gave to the sea His decree,  <paragraph-break/>That the waters should not transgress His commandment,  <paragraph-break/>When He appointed the foundations of the earth;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>30</verse-number>Then I was by Him, as a nursling;  <paragraph-break/>And I was daily all delight,  <paragraph-break/>Playing always before Him,  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>31</verse-number>Playing in His habitable earth,  <paragraph-break/>And my delights are with the sons of men.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>32</verse-number>Now therefore, ye children, hearken unto me;  <paragraph-break/>For happy are they that keep my ways.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>33</verse-number>Hear instruction, and be wise,  <paragraph-break/>And refuse it not.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>34</verse-number>Happy is the man that hearkeneth to me,  <paragraph-break/>Watching daily at my gates, waiting at the posts of my doors.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>35</verse-number>For whoso findeth me findeth life,  <paragraph-break/>And obtaineth favour of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>36</verse-number>But he that misseth me wrongeth his own soul;  <paragraph-break/>All they that hate me love death.’  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>9</chapter-number>Wisdom hath builded her house,  She hath hewn out her seven  pillars;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>She hath prepared her meat, she hath mingled her wine;  <paragraph-break/>She hath also furnished her table.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>She hath sent forth her maidens, she calleth,  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>Upon the highest places of the city:  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>‘Whoso is thoughtless, let him turn in hither’;  <paragraph-break/>As for him that lacketh understanding, she saith to him:  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>‘Come, eat of my bread,  <paragraph-break/>And drink of the wine which I have mingled.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Forsake all thoughtlessness, and live;  <paragraph-break/>And walk in the way of understanding.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>He that correcteth a scorner getteth to himself shame,  <paragraph-break/>And he that reproveth a wicked man, it becometh unto him a blot.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>Reprove not a scorner, lest he hate thee;  <paragraph-break/>Reprove a wise man, and he will love thee.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>Give to a wise man, and he will be yet wiser;  <paragraph-break/>Teach a righteous man, and he will increase in learning.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>The fear of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> is the beginning of wisdom,  <paragraph-break/>And the knowledge of the All-holy is understanding.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>For by me thy days shall be multiplied,  <paragraph-break/>And the years of thy life shall be increased.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>If thou art wise, thou art wise for thyself;  <paragraph-break/>And if thou scornest, thou alone shalt bear it.’  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>The woman Folly is riotous;  
         <paragraph-break/>She is thoughtless, and knoweth nothing.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>And she sitteth at the door of her house,  <paragraph-break/>On a seat in the high places of the city,  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>To call to them that pass by,  <paragraph-break/>Who go right on their ways:  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>‘Whoso is thoughtless, let him turn in hither’;  <paragraph-break/>And as for him that lacketh understanding, she saith to him:  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>‘Stolen waters are sweet,  <paragraph-break/>And bread eaten in secret is pleasant.’  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>But he knoweth not that the shades are there;  <paragraph-break/>That her guests are in the depths of the nether-world.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>10</chapter-number>The proverbs of Solomon.   <paragraph-break/>A wise son maketh a glad father;  <paragraph-break/>But a foolish son is the grief of his mother.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>Treasures of wickedness profit nothing;  <paragraph-break/>But righteousness delivereth from death.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>The <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> will not suffer the soul of the righteous to famish;  <paragraph-break/>But He thrusteth away the desire of the wicked.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>He becometh poor that dealeth with a slack hand;  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>But the hand of the diligent maketh rich.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>A wise son gathereth in summer;  <paragraph-break/>But a son that doeth shamefully sleepeth in harvest.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Blessings are upon the head of the righteous;  <paragraph-break/>But the mouth of the wicked concealeth violence.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>The memory of the righteous shall be for a blessing;  <paragraph-break/>But the name of the wicked shall rot.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>The wise in heart will receive commandments;  <paragraph-break/>But a prating fool shall fall.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>He that walketh uprightly walketh securely;  <paragraph-break/>But he that perverteth his ways shall be found out.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>He that winketh with the eye causeth sorrow;  <paragraph-break/>And a prating fool shall fall.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>The mouth of the righteous is a fountain of life;  <paragraph-break/>But the mouth of the wicked concealeth violence.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>Hatred stirreth up strifes;  <paragraph-break/>But love covereth all transgressions.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>In the lips of him that hath discernment wisdom is found;  <paragraph-break/>But a rod is for the back of him that is void of understanding.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>Wise men lay up knowledge;  <paragraph-break/>But the mouth of the foolish is an imminent ruin.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>The rich man’s wealth is his strong city;  <paragraph-break/>The ruin of the poor is their poverty.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>The wages of the righteous is life;  <paragraph-break/>The increase of the wicked is sin.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>He is in the way of life that heedeth instruction;  <paragraph-break/>But he that forsaketh reproof erreth.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>He that hideth hatred is of lying lips;  <paragraph-break/>And he that uttereth a slander is a fool.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>In the multitude of words there wanteth not transgression;  <paragraph-break/>But he that refraineth his lips is wise.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>The tongue of the righteous is as choice silver;  <paragraph-break/>The heart of the wicked is little worth.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>The lips of the righteous feed many;  <paragraph-break/>But the foolish die for want of understanding.  <paragraph-break/>
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>The blessing of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>, it maketh rich,  <paragraph-break/>And toil addeth nothing thereto.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>It is as sport to a fool to do wickedness,  <paragraph-break/>And so is wisdom to a man of discernment.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>The fear of the wicked, it shall come upon him;  <paragraph-break/>And the desire of the righteous shall be granted.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>When the whirlwind passeth, the wicked is no more;  <paragraph-break/>But the righteous is an everlasting foundation.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>As vinegar to the teeth, and as smoke to the eyes,  <paragraph-break/>So is the sluggard to them that send him.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>The fear of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> prolongeth days;  <paragraph-break/>But the years of the wicked shall be shortened.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>The hope of the righteous is gladness;  <paragraph-break/>But the expectation of the wicked shall perish.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>29</verse-number>The way of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> is a stronghold to the upright,  <paragraph-break/>But ruin to the workers of iniquity.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>30</verse-number>The righteous shall never be moved;  <paragraph-break/>But the wicked shall not inhabit the land.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>31</verse-number>The mouth of the righteous buddeth with wisdom;  <paragraph-break/>But the froward tongue shall be cut off.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>32</verse-number>The lips of the righteous know what is acceptable;  <paragraph-break/>But the mouth of the wicked is all frowardness.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>11</chapter-number>A false balance is an  abomination to the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>;  <paragraph-break/>But a perfect weight is His delight.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>When pride cometh, then cometh shame;  <paragraph-break/>But with the lowly is wisdom.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>The integrity of the upright shall guide them;  <paragraph-break/>But the perverseness of the faithless shall destroy them.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>Riches profit not in the day of wrath;  <paragraph-break/>But righteousness delivereth from death.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>The righteousness of the sincere shall make straight his way;  <paragraph-break/>But the wicked shall fall by his own wickedness.  <paragraph-break/>
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>The righteousness of the upright shall deliver them;  <paragraph-break/>But the faithless shall be trapped in their own crafty device.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>When a wicked man dieth, his expectation shall perish,  <paragraph-break/>And the hope of strength perisheth.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>The righteous is delivered out of trouble,  <paragraph-break/>And the wicked cometh in his stead.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>With his mouth the impious man destroyeth his neighbour;  <paragraph-break/>But through knowledge shall the righteous be delivered.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>When it goeth well with the righteous, the city rejoiceth;  <paragraph-break/>And when the wicked perish, there is joy.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>By the blessing of the upright a city is exalted;  <paragraph-break/>But it is overthrown by the mouth of the wicked.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>He that despiseth his neighbour lacketh understanding;  <paragraph-break/>But a man of discernment holdeth his peace.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>He that goeth about as a talebearer revealeth secrets;  <paragraph-break/>But he that is of a faithful spirit concealeth a matter.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>Where no wise direction is, a people falleth;  <paragraph-break/>But in the multitude of counsellors there is safety.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>He that is surety for a stranger shall smart for it;  <paragraph-break/>But he that hateth them that strike hands is secure.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>A gracious woman obtaineth honour;  <paragraph-break/>And strong men obtain riches.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>The merciful man doeth good to his own soul;  <paragraph-break/>But he that is cruel troubleth his own flesh.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>The wicked earneth deceitful wages;  <paragraph-break/>But he that soweth righteousness hath a sure reward.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>Stedfast righteousness tendeth to life;  <paragraph-break/>But he that pursueth evil pursueth it to his own death.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>They that are perverse in heart are an abomination to the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>;  <paragraph-break/>But such as are upright in their way are His delight.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>My hand upon it! the evil man shall not be unpunished;  <paragraph-break/>But the seed of the righteous shall escape.  <paragraph-break/>
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>As a ring of gold in a swine’s snout, so is a fair woman that turneth aside from discretion.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>The desire of the righteous is only good;  <paragraph-break/>But the expectation of the wicked is wrath.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>There is that scattereth, and yet increaseth;  <paragraph-break/>And there is that withholdeth more than is meet, but it tendeth only to want.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>The beneficent soul shall be made rich, and he that satisfieth abundantly shall be satisfied also himself.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>He that withholdeth corn, the people shall curse him;  <paragraph-break/>But blessing shall be upon the head of him that selleth it.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>He that diligently seeketh good seeketh favour;  <paragraph-break/>But he that searcheth for evil, it shall come unto him.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>He that trusteth in his riches shall fall;  <paragraph-break/>But the righteous shall flourish as foliage.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>29</verse-number>He that troubleth his own house shall inherit the wind;  <paragraph-break/>And the foolish shall be servant to the wise of heart.  
         <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>30</verse-number>The fruit of the righteous is a tree of life;  <paragraph-break/>And he that is wise winneth souls.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>31</verse-number>Behold, the righteous shall be requited in the earth;  <paragraph-break/>How much more the wicked and the sinner!  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>12</chapter-number>Whoso loveth knowledge  loveth correction;  <paragraph-break/>But he that is brutish hateth reproof.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>A good man shall obtain favour of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>;  <paragraph-break/>But a man of wicked devices will He condemn.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>A man shall not be established by wickedness;  <paragraph-break/>But the root of the righteous shall never be moved.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>A virtuous woman is a crown to her husband;  <paragraph-break/>But she that doeth shamefully is as rottenness in his bones.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>The thoughts of the righteous are right;  <paragraph-break/>But the counsels of the wicked are deceit.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>The words of the wicked are to lie in wait for blood;  <paragraph-break/>But the mouth of the upright shall deliver them.  <paragraph-break/> 
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>The wicked are overthrown, and are not;  <paragraph-break/>But the house of the righteous shall stand.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>A man shall be commended according to his intelligence;  <paragraph-break/>But he that is of a distorted understanding shall be despised.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>Better is he that is lightly esteemed, and hath a servant,  <paragraph-break/>Than he that playeth the man of rank, and lacketh bread.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>A righteous man regardeth the life of his beast;  <paragraph-break/>But the tender mercies of the wicked are cruel.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>He that tilleth his ground shall have plenty of bread;  <paragraph-break/>But he that followeth after vain things is void of understanding.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>The wicked desireth the prey of evil men;  <paragraph-break/>But the root of the righteous yieldeth fruit.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>In the transgression of the lips is a snare to the evil man;  <paragraph-break/>But the righteous cometh out of trouble.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>A man shall be satisfied with good by the fruit of his mouth,  <paragraph-break/>And the doings of a man’s hands shall be rendered unto him.  
         <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>The way of a fool is straight in his own eyes;  <paragraph-break/>But he that is wise hearkeneth unto counsel.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>A fool’s vexation is presently known;  <paragraph-break/>But a prudent man concealeth shame.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>He that breatheth forth truth uttereth righteousness;  <paragraph-break/>But a false witness deceit.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>There is that speaketh like the piercings of a sword;  <paragraph-break/>But the tongue of the wise is health.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>The lip of truth shall be established for ever;  <paragraph-break/>But a lying tongue is but for a moment.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>Deceit is in the heart of them that devise evil;  <paragraph-break/>But to the counsellors of peace is joy.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>There shall no mischief befall the righteous;  <paragraph-break/>But the wicked are filled with evil.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>Lying lips are an abomination to the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>;  <paragraph-break/>But they that deal truly are His delight.  <paragraph-break/>
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>A prudent man concealeth knowledge;  <paragraph-break/>But the heart of fools proclaimeth foolishness.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>The hand of the diligent shall bear rule;  <paragraph-break/>But the slothful shall be under tribute.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>Care in the heart of a man boweth it down;  <paragraph-break/>But a good word maketh it glad.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>The righteous is guided by his friend;  <paragraph-break/>But the way of the wicked leadeth them astray.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>The slothful man shall not hunt his prey;  <paragraph-break/>But the precious substance of men is to be diligent.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>In the way of righteousness is life,  <paragraph-break/>And in the pathway thereof there is no death.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>13</chapter-number>A wise son is instructed of his  father;  <paragraph-break/>But a scorner heareth not rebuke.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>A man shall eat good from the fruit of his mouth;  <paragraph-break/>But the desire of the faithless is violence.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>He that guardeth his mouth keepeth his life;  
         <paragraph-break/>But for him that openeth wide his lips there shall be ruin.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>The soul of the sluggard desireth, and hath nothing;  <paragraph-break/>But the soul of the diligent shall be abundantly gratified.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>A righteous man hateth lying;  <paragraph-break/>But a wicked man behaveth vilely and shamefully.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Righteousness guardeth him that is upright in the way;  <paragraph-break/>But wickedness overthroweth the sinner.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>There is that pretendeth himself rich, yet hath nothing;  <paragraph-break/>There is that pretendeth himself poor, yet hath great wealth.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>The ransom of a man’s life are his riches;  <paragraph-break/>But the poor heareth no threatening.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>The light of the righteous rejoiceth;  <paragraph-break/>But the lamp of the wicked shall be put out.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>By pride cometh only contention;  <paragraph-break/>But with the well-advised is wisdom.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>Wealth gotten by vanity shall be diminished;  <paragraph-break/>But he that gathereth little by little shall increase.  <paragraph-break/> 
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>Hope deferred maketh the heart sick;  <paragraph-break/>But desire fulfilled is a tree of life.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>Whoso despiseth the word shall suffer thereby;  <paragraph-break/>But he that feareth the commandment shall be rewarded.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>The teaching of the wise is a fountain of life,  <paragraph-break/>To depart from the snares of death.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>Good understanding giveth grace;  <paragraph-break/>But the way of the faithless is harsh.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>Every prudent man dealeth with forethought;  <paragraph-break/>But a fool unfoldeth folly.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>A wicked messenger falleth into evil;  <paragraph-break/>But a faithful ambassador is health.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>Poverty and shame shall be to him that refuseth instruction;  <paragraph-break/>But he that regardeth reproof shall be honoured.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>The desire accomplished is sweet to the soul;  <paragraph-break/>And it is an abomination to fools to depart from evil. <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>He that walketh with wise men shall be wise;  <paragraph-break/>But the companion of fools shall smart for it.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>Evil pursueth sinners;  <paragraph-break/>But to the righteous good shall be repaid.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>A good man leaveth an inheritance to his children’s children;  <paragraph-break/>And the wealth of the sinner is laid up for the righteous.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>Much food is in the tillage of the poor;  <paragraph-break/>But there is that is swept away by want of righteousness.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>He that spareth his rod hateth his son;  <paragraph-break/>But he that loveth him chasteneth him betimes.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>The righteous eateth to the satisfying of his desire;  <paragraph-break/>But the belly of the wicked shall want.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>14</chapter-number>Every wise woman buildeth her house;  <paragraph-break/>But the foolish plucketh it down with her hands.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>He that walketh in his uprightness feareth the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>;  <paragraph-break/>But he that is perverse in his ways despiseth Him.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>In the mouth of the foolish is a rod of pride;  <paragraph-break/>But the lips of the wise shall preserve them.  <paragraph-break/> 
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>Where no oxen are, the crib is clean;  <paragraph-break/>But much increase is by the strength of the ox.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>A faithful witness will not lie;  <paragraph-break/>But a false witness breatheth forth lies.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>A scorner seeketh wisdom, and findeth it not;  <paragraph-break/>But knowledge is easy unto him that hath discernment.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>Go from the presence of a foolish man, for thou wilt not perceive the lips of knowledge.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>The wisdom of the prudent is to look well to his way;  <paragraph-break/>But the folly of fools is deceit.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>Amends pleadeth for fools;  <paragraph-break/>But among the upright there is good will.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>The heart knoweth its own bitterness;  <paragraph-break/>And with its joy no stranger can intermeddle.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>The house of the wicked shall be overthrown;  <paragraph-break/>But the tent of the upright shall flourish.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>There is a way which seemeth right unto a man,  
         <paragraph-break/>But the end thereof are the ways of death.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>Even in laughter the heart acheth;  <paragraph-break/>And the end of mirth is heaviness.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>The dissembler in heart shall have his fill from his own ways;  <paragraph-break/>And a good man shall be satisfied from himself.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>The thoughtless believeth every word;  <paragraph-break/>But the prudent man looketh well to his going.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>A wise man feareth, and departeth from evil;  <paragraph-break/>But the fool behaveth overbearingly, and is confident.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>He that is soon angry dealeth foolishly;  <paragraph-break/>And a man of wicked devices is hated.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>The thoughtless come into possession of folly;  <paragraph-break/>But the prudent are crowned with knowledge.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>The evil bow before the good,  <paragraph-break/>And the wicked at the gates of the righteous.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>The poor is hated even of his own neighbour;  <paragraph-break/>But the rich hath many friends.  <paragraph-break/> 
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>He that despiseth his neighbour sinneth;  <paragraph-break/>But he that is gracious unto the humble, happy is he.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>Shall they not go astray that devise evil? But mercy and truth shall be for them that devise good.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>In all labour there is profit;  <paragraph-break/>But the talk of the lips tendeth only to penury.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>The crown of the wise is their riches;  <paragraph-break/>But the folly of fools remaineth folly.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>A true witness delivereth souls;  <paragraph-break/>But he that breatheth forth lies is all deceit.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>In the fear of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> a man hath strong confidence;  <paragraph-break/>And his children shall have a place of refuge.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>The fear of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> is a fountain of life, to depart from the snares of death.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>In the multitude of people is the king’s glory;  <paragraph-break/>But in the want of people is the ruin of the prince.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>29</verse-number>He that is slow to anger is of great understanding;  
         <paragraph-break/>But he that is hasty of spirit exalteth folly.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>30</verse-number>A tranquil heart is the life of the flesh;  <paragraph-break/>But envy is the rottenness of the bones.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>31</verse-number>He that oppresseth the poor blasphemeth his Maker;  <paragraph-break/>But he that is gracious unto the needy honoureth Him.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>32</verse-number>The wicked is thrust down in his misfortune;  <paragraph-break/>But the righteous, even when he is brought to death, hath hope.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>33</verse-number>In the heart of him that hath discernment wisdom resteth;  <paragraph-break/>But in the inward part of fools it maketh itself known.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>34</verse-number>Righteousness exalteth a nation;  <paragraph-break/>But sin is a reproach to any people.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>35</verse-number>The king’s favour is toward a servant that dealeth wisely;  <paragraph-break/>But his wrath striketh him that dealeth shamefully.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>15</chapter-number>A soft answer turneth away  wrath;  <paragraph-break/>But a grievous word stirreth up anger.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>The tongue of the wise useth knowledge aright;  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>But the mouth of fools poureth out foolishness.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>The eyes of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> are in every place,  <paragraph-break/>Keeping watch upon the evil and the good.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>A soothing tongue is a tree of life;  <paragraph-break/>But perverseness therein is a wound to the spirit.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>A fool despiseth his father’s correction;  <paragraph-break/>But he that regardeth reproof is prudent.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>In the house of the righteous is much treasure;  <paragraph-break/>But in the revenues of the wicked is trouble.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>The lips of the wise disperse knowledge;  <paragraph-break/>But the heart of the foolish is not stedfast.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>The sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination to the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>;  <paragraph-break/>But the prayer of the upright is His delight.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>The way of the wicked is an abomination to the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>;  <paragraph-break/>But He loveth him that followeth after righteousness.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>There is grievous correction for him that forsaketh the way;  
         <paragraph-break/>And he that hateth reproof shall die.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>The nether-world and Destruction are before the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>;  <paragraph-break/>How much more then the hearts of the children of men!  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>A scorner loveth not to be reproved;  <paragraph-break/>He will not go unto the wise.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>A merry heart maketh a cheerful countenance;  <paragraph-break/>But by sorrow of heart the spirit is broken.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>The heart of him that hath discernment seeketh knowledge;  <paragraph-break/>But the mouth of fools feedeth on folly.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>All the days of the poor are evil;  <paragraph-break/>But he that is of a merry heart hath a continual feast.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>Better is little with the fear of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>,  <paragraph-break/>Than great treasure and turmoil therewith.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>Better is a dinner of herbs where love is,  <paragraph-break/>Than a stalled ox and hatred therewith.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>A wrathful man stirreth up discord;  <paragraph-break/>But he that is slow to anger appeaseth strife.  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>The way of the sluggard is as though hedged by thorns;  <paragraph-break/>But the path of the upright is even.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>A wise son maketh a glad father;  <paragraph-break/>But a foolish man despiseth his mother.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>Folly is joy to him that lacketh understanding;  <paragraph-break/>But a man of discernment walketh straightforwards.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>For want of counsel purposes are frustrated;  <paragraph-break/>But in the multitude of counsellors they are established.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>A man hath joy in the answer of his mouth;  <paragraph-break/>And a word in due season, how good is it!  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>The path of life goeth upward for the wise, that he may depart from the nether-world beneath.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>The <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> will pluck up the house of the proud;  <paragraph-break/>But He will establish the border of the widow.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>The thoughts of wickedness are an abomination to the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>;  <paragraph-break/>But words of pleasantness are pure.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>He that is greedy of gain troubleth his own house;  
         <paragraph-break/>But he that hateth gifts shall live.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>The heart of the righteous studieth to answer;  <paragraph-break/>But the mouth of the wicked poureth out evil things.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>29</verse-number>The <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> is far from the wicked;  <paragraph-break/>But He heareth the prayer of the righteous.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>30</verse-number>The light of the eyes rejoiceth the heart;  <paragraph-break/>And a good report maketh the bones fat.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>31</verse-number>The ear that hearkeneth to the reproof of life abideth among the wise.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>32</verse-number>He that refuseth correction despiseth his own soul;  <paragraph-break/>But he that hearkeneth to reproof getteth understanding.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>33</verse-number>The fear of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> is the instruction of wisdom;  <paragraph-break/>And before honour goeth humility.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>16</chapter-number>The preparations of the heart  are man’s,  <paragraph-break/>But the answer of the tongue is from the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>All the ways of a man are clean in his own eyes;  <paragraph-break/>But the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> weigheth the spirits.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>Commit thy works unto the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>,  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>And thy thoughts shall be established.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>The <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> hath made every things for His own purpose,  <paragraph-break/>Yea, even the wicked for the day of evil.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Every one that is proud in heart is an abomination to the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>;  <paragraph-break/>My hand upon it! he shall not be unpunished.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>By mercy and truth iniquity is expiated;  <paragraph-break/>And by the fear of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> men depart from evil.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>When a man’s ways please the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>,  <paragraph-break/>He maketh even his enemies to be at peace with him.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>Better is a little with righteousness  <paragraph-break/>Than great revenues with injustice.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>A man’s heart deviseth his way;  <paragraph-break/>But the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> directeth his steps.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>A divine sentence is in the lips of the king;  <paragraph-break/>His mouth trespasseth not in judgment.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>A just balance and scales are the <small-caps>Lord’s</small-caps>;  <paragraph-break/>All the weights of the bag are His work.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>It is an abomination to kings to commit wickedness;  <paragraph-break/>For the throne is established by righteousness.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>Righteous lips are the delight of kings;  <paragraph-break/>And they love him that speaketh right.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>The wrath of a king is as messengers of death;  <paragraph-break/>But a wise man will pacify it.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>In the light of the king’s countenance is life;  <paragraph-break/>And his favour is as a cloud of the latter rain.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>How much better is it to get wisdom than gold!  <paragraph-break/>Yea, to get understanding is rather to be chosen than silver.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>The highway of the upright is to depart from evil;  <paragraph-break/>He that keepeth his way preserveth his soul.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>Pride goeth before destruction,  <paragraph-break/>And a haughty spirit before a fall.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>Better it is to be of a lowly spirit with the humble,  <paragraph-break/>Than to divide the spoil with the proud.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>He that giveth heed unto the word shall find good;  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>And whoso trusteth in the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>, happy is he.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>The wise in heart is called a man of discernment;  <paragraph-break/>And the sweetness of the lips increaseth learning.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>Understanding is a fountain of life unto him that hath it;  <paragraph-break/>But folly is the chastisement of fools.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>The heart of the wise teacheth his mouth,  <paragraph-break/>And addeth learning to his lips.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>Pleasant words are as a honeycomb,  <paragraph-break/>Sweet to the soul, and health to the bones.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>There is a way which seemeth right unto a man,  <paragraph-break/>But the end thereof are the ways of death.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>The hunger of the labouring man laboureth for him;  <paragraph-break/>For his mouth compelleth him.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>An ungodly man diggeth up evil,  <paragraph-break/>And in his lips there is as a burning fire.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>A froward man soweth strife;  <paragraph-break/>And a whisperer separateth familiar friends.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>29</verse-number>A man of violence enticeth his neighbour,  <paragraph-break/>And leadeth him into a way that is not good.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>30</verse-number>He shutteth his eyes, it is to devise froward things;  <paragraph-break/>He that biteth his lips bringeth evil to pass.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>31</verse-number>The hoary head is a crown of glory,  <paragraph-break/>It is found in the way of righteousness.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>32</verse-number>He that is slow to anger is better than the mighty;  <paragraph-break/>And he that ruleth his spirit than he that taketh a city.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>33</verse-number>The lot is cast into the lap;  <paragraph-break/>But the whole disposing thereof is of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>17</chapter-number>Better is a dry morsel and  quietness therewith,  <paragraph-break/>Than a house full of feasting with strife.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>A servant that dealeth wisely shall have rule over a son that dealeth shamefully,  <paragraph-break/>And shall have part of the inheritance among the brethren.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>The refining pot is for silver, and the furnace for gold;  <paragraph-break/>But the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> trieth the hearts.  <paragraph-break/> 
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>A evil-doer giveth heed to wicked lips;  <paragraph-break/>And a liar giveth ear to a mischievous tongue.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Whoso mocketh the poor blasphemeth his Maker;  <paragraph-break/>And he that is glad at calamity shall not be unpunished.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Children’s children are the crown of old men;  <paragraph-break/>And the glory of children are their fathers.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>Overbearing speech becometh not a churl;  <paragraph-break/>Much less do lying lips a prince.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>A gift is as a precious stone in the eyes of him that hath it;  <paragraph-break/>Whithersoever he turneth, he prospereth.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>He that covereth a transgression seeketh love;  <paragraph-break/>But he that harpeth on a matter estrangeth a familiar friend.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>A rebuke entereth deeper into a man of understanding  <paragraph-break/>Than a hundred stripes into a fool.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>A rebellious man seeketh only evil;  <paragraph-break/>Therefore a cruel messenger shall be sent against him.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>Let a bear robbed of her whelps meet a man,  <paragraph-break/>Rather than a fool in his folly.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>Whoso rewardeth evil for good,  <paragraph-break/>Evil shall not depart from his house.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>The beginning of strife is as when one letteth out water;  <paragraph-break/>Therefore leave off contention, before the quarrel break out.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>He that justifieth the wicked, and he that condemneth the righteous,  <paragraph-break/>Even they both are an abomination to the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>Wherefore is there a price in the hand of a fool  <paragraph-break/>To buy wisdom, seeing he hath no understanding?  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>A friend loveth at all times,  <paragraph-break/>And a brother is born for adversity.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>A man void of understanding is he that striketh hands,  <paragraph-break/>And becometh surety in the presence of his neighbour.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>He loveth transgression that loveth strife;  <paragraph-break/>He that exalteth his gate seeketh destruction.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>He that hath a froward heart findeth no good;  <paragraph-break/>And he that hath a perverse tongue falleth into evil.  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>He that begetteth a fool doeth it to his sorrow;  <paragraph-break/>And the father of a churl hath no joy.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>A merry heart is a good medicine;  <paragraph-break/>But a broken spirit drieth the bones.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>A wicked man taketh a gift out of the bosom,  <paragraph-break/>To pervert the ways of justice.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>Wisdom is before him that hath understanding;  <paragraph-break/>But the eyes of a fool are in the ends of the earth.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>A foolish son is vexation to his father,  <paragraph-break/>And bitterness to her that bore him.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>To punish also the righteous is not good,  <paragraph-break/>Nor to strike the noble for their uprightness.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>He that spareth his words hath knowledge;  <paragraph-break/>And he that husbandeth his spirit is a man of discernment.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>Even a fool, when he holdeth his peace, is counted wise;  <paragraph-break/>And he that shutteth his lips is esteemed as a man of understanding.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>18</chapter-number>He that separateth himself  seeketh his own desire,  <paragraph-break/>And snarlest against all sound wisdom.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>A fool hath no delight in understanding,  <paragraph-break/>But only that his heart may lay itself bare.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>When the wicked cometh, there cometh also contempt,  <paragraph-break/>And with ignominy reproach.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>The words of a man’s mouth are as deep waters;  <paragraph-break/>A flowing brook, a fountain of wisdom.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>It is not good to respect the person of the wicked,  <paragraph-break/>So as to turn aside the righteous in judgment.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>A fool’s lips enter into contention,  <paragraph-break/>And his mouth calleth for strokes.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>A fool’s mouth is his ruin,  <paragraph-break/>And his lips are the snare of his soul.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>The words of a whisperer are as dainty morsels,  <paragraph-break/>And they go down into the innermost parts of the belly.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>Even one that is slack in his work  <paragraph-break/>Is brother to him that is a destroyer.  <paragraph-break/>
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>The name of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> is a strong tower:  <paragraph-break/>The righteous runneth into it, and is set up on high.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>The rich man’s wealth is his strong city,  <paragraph-break/>And as a high wall in his own conceit.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>Before destruction the heart of a man is haughty,  <paragraph-break/>And before honour goeth humility.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>He that giveth answer before he heareth,  <paragraph-break/>It is folly and confusion unto him.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>The spirit of a man will sustain his infirmity;  <paragraph-break/>But a broken spirit who can bear?  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>The heart of the prudent getteth knowledge;  <paragraph-break/>And the ear of the wise seeketh knowledge.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>A man’s gift maketh room for him,  <paragraph-break/>And bringeth him before great men.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>He that pleadeth his cause first seemeth just;  <paragraph-break/>But his neighbour cometh and searcheth him out.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>The lot causeth strife to cease,  <paragraph-break/>And parteth asunder the contentious.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>A brother offended is harder to be won than a strong city;  <paragraph-break/>And their contentions are like the bars of a castle.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>A man’s belly shall be filled with the fruit of his mouth;  <paragraph-break/>With the increase of his lips shall he be satisfied.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>Death and life are in the power of the tongue;  <paragraph-break/>And they that indulge it shall eat the fruit thereof.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>Whoso findeth a wife findeth a great good,  <paragraph-break/>And obtaineth favour of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>The poor useth entreaties;  <paragraph-break/>But the rich answereth impudently.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>There are friends that one hath to his own hurt;  <paragraph-break/>But there is a friend that sticketh closer than a brother.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>19</chapter-number>Better is the poor that walketh  in his integrity  <paragraph-break/>Than he that is perverse in his lips and a fool at the same time.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>Also, that the soul be without knowledge is not good;  <paragraph-break/>And he that hasteth with his feet sinneth.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>The foolishness of man perverteth his way;  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>And his heart fretteth against the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>Wealth addeth many friends;  <paragraph-break/>But as for the poor, his friend separateth himself from him.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>A false witness shall not be unpunished;  <paragraph-break/>And he that breatheth forth lies shall not escape.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Many will entreat the favour of the liberal man;  <paragraph-break/>And every man is a friend to him that giveth gifts.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>All the brethren of the poor do hate him;  <paragraph-break/>How much more do his friends go far from him!  <paragraph-break/>He that pursueth words, they turn against him.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>He that getteth wisdom loveth his own soul;  <paragraph-break/>He that keepeth understanding shall find good.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>A false witness shall not be unpunished;  <paragraph-break/>And he that breatheth forth lies shall perish.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>Luxury is not seemly for a fool;  <paragraph-break/>Much less for a servant to have rule over princes.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>It is the discretion of a man to be slow to anger,  <paragraph-break/>And it is his glory to pass over a transgression.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>The king’s wrath is as the roaring of a lion;  <paragraph-break/>But his favour is as dew upon the grass.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>A foolish son is the calamity of his father;  <paragraph-break/>And the contentions of a wife are a continual dropping.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>House and riches are the inheritance of fathers;  <paragraph-break/>But a prudent wife is from the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>Slothfulness casteth into a deep sleep;  <paragraph-break/>And the idle soul shall suffer hunger.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>He that keepeth the commandment keepeth his soul;  <paragraph-break/>But he that despiseth His ways shall die.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>He that is gracious unto the poor lendeth unto the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>;  <paragraph-break/>And his good deed will He repay unto him.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>Chasten thy son, for there is hope;  <paragraph-break/>But set not thy heart on his destruction.  <paragraph-break/> 
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>A man of great wrath shall suffer punishment;  <paragraph-break/>For if thou interpose, thou wilt add thereto.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>Hear counsel, and receive instruction,  <paragraph-break/>That thou mayest be wise in thy latter end.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>There are many devices in a man’s heart;  <paragraph-break/>But the counsel of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>, that shall stand.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>The lust of a man is his shame;  <paragraph-break/>And a poor man is better than a liar.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>The fear of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> tendeth to life;  <paragraph-break/>And he that hath it shall abide satisfied,  <paragraph-break/>He shall not be visited with evil.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>The sluggard burieth his hand in the dish,  <paragraph-break/>And will not so much as bring it back to his mouth.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>When thou smitest a scorner, the simple will become prudent;  <paragraph-break/>And when one that hath understanding is reproved, he will understand knowledge.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>A son that dealeth shamefully and reproachfully  <paragraph-break/>Will despoil his father, and chase away his mother.  
         <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>Cease, my son, to hear the instruction  <paragraph-break/>That causeth to err from the words of knowledge.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>An ungodly witness mocketh at right;  <paragraph-break/>And the mouth of the wicked devoureth iniquity.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>29</verse-number>Judgments are prepared for scorners,  <paragraph-break/>And stripes for the back of fools.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>20</chapter-number>Wine is a mocker, strong drink  is riotous;  <paragraph-break/>And whosoever reeleth thereby is not wise.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>The terror of a king is as the roaring of a lion:  <paragraph-break/>He that provoketh him to anger forfeiteth his life.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>It is an honour for a man to keep aloof from strife;  <paragraph-break/>But every fool will be snarling.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>The sluggard will not plow when winter setteth in;  <paragraph-break/>Therefore he shall beg in harvest, and have nothing.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Counsel in the heart of man is like deep water;  <paragraph-break/>But a man of understanding will draw it out.  <paragraph-break/> 
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Most men will proclaim every one his own goodness;  <paragraph-break/>But a faithful man who can find?  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>He that walketh in his integrity as a just man,  <paragraph-break/>Happy are his children after him.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>A king that sitteth on the throne of judgment  <paragraph-break/>Scattereth away all evil with his eyes.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>Who can say: ‘I have made my heart clean,  <paragraph-break/>I am pure from my sin’?  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>Divers weights, and divers measures,  <paragraph-break/>Both of them alike are abomination to the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>Even a child is known by his doings,  <paragraph-break/>Whether his work be pure, and whether it be right.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>The hearing ear, and the seeing eye,  <paragraph-break/>The <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> hath made even both of them.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>Love not sleep, lest thou come to poverty;  <paragraph-break/>Open thine eyes, and thou shalt have bread in plenty.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>‘It is bad, it is bad’, saith the buyer;  
         <paragraph-break/>But when he is gone his way, then he boasteth.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>There is gold, and a multitude of rubies;  <paragraph-break/>But the lips of knowledge are a precious jewel.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>Take his garment that is surety for a stranger;  <paragraph-break/>And hold him in pledge that is surety for an alien woman.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>Bread of falsehood is sweet to a man;  <paragraph-break/>But afterwards his mouth shall be filled with gravel.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>Every purpose is established by counsel;  <paragraph-break/>And with good advice carry on war.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>He that goeth about as a talebearer revealeth secrets;  <paragraph-break/>Therefore meddle not with him that openeth wide his lips.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>Whoso curseth his father or his mother,  <paragraph-break/>His lamp shall be put out in the blackest darkness.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>An estate may be gotten hastily at the beginning;  <paragraph-break/>But the end thereof shall not be blessed.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>Say not thou: ‘I will requite evil’;  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>Wait for the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>, and He will save thee.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>Divers weights are an abomination to the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>;  <paragraph-break/>And a false balance is not good.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>A man’s goings are of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>;  <paragraph-break/>How then can man look to his way?  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>It is a snare to a man rashly to say: ‘Holy’,  <paragraph-break/>And after vows to make inquiry.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>A wise king sifteth the wicked,  <paragraph-break/>And turneth the wheel over them.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>The spirit of man is the lamp of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>,  <paragraph-break/>Searching all the inward parts.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>Mercy and truth preserve the king;  <paragraph-break/>And his throne is upheld by mercy.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>29</verse-number>The glory of young men is their strength;  <paragraph-break/>And the beauty of old men is the hoary head.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>30</verse-number>Sharp wounds cleanse away evil;  <paragraph-break/>So do stripes that reach the inward parts.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>21</chapter-number>The king’s heart is in the hand  of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>, as the        watercourses:  <paragraph-break/>He turneth it whithersoever He will.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>Every way of a man is right in his own eyes;  <paragraph-break/>But the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> weigheth the hearts.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>To do righteousness and justice  <paragraph-break/>Is more acceptable to the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> than sacrifice.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>A haughty look, and a proud heart— <paragraph-break/>The tillage of the wicked is sin.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>The thoughts of the diligent tend only to plenteousness;  <paragraph-break/>But every one that is hasty hasteth only to want.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>The getting of treasures by a lying tongue  <paragraph-break/>Is a vapour driven to and fro; they [that seek them] seek death.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>The violence of the wicked shall drag them away;  <paragraph-break/>Because they refuse to do justly.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>The way of man is froward and strange;  <paragraph-break/>But as for the pure, his work is right.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>It is better to dwell in a corner of the housetop,  <paragraph-break/>Than in a house in common with a contentious woman.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>The soul of the wicked desireth evil;  <paragraph-break/>His neighbour findeth no favour in his eyes.  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>When the scorner is punished, the thoughtless is made wise;  <paragraph-break/>And when the wise is instructed, he receiveth knowledge.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>The Righteous One considereth the house of the wicked;  <paragraph-break/>Overthrowing the wicked to their ruin.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>Whoso stoppeth his ears at the cry of the poor,  <paragraph-break/>He also shall cry himself, but shall not be answered.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>A gift in secret pacifieth anger,  <paragraph-break/>And a present in the bosom strong wrath.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>To do justly is joy to the righteous,  <paragraph-break/>But ruin to the workers of iniquity.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>The man that strayeth out of the way of understanding  <paragraph-break/>Shall rest in the congregation of the shades.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>He that loveth pleasure shall be a poor man;  <paragraph-break/>He that loveth wine and oil shall not be rich.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>The wicked is a ransom for the righteous;  <paragraph-break/>And the faithless cometh in the stead of the upright.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>It is better to dwell in a desert land,  <paragraph-break/>Than with a contentious and fretful woman.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>There is desirable treasure and oil in the dwelling of the wise;  <paragraph-break/>But a foolish man swalloweth it up.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>He that followeth after righteousness and mercy  <paragraph-break/>Findeth life, prosperity, and honour.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>A wise man scaleth the city of the mighty,  <paragraph-break/>And bringeth down the stronghold wherein it trusteth.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>Whoso keepeth his mouth and his tongue  <paragraph-break/>Keepeth his soul from troubles.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>A proud and haughty man, scorner is his name,  <paragraph-break/>Even he that dealeth in overbearing pride.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>The desire of the slothful killeth him;  <paragraph-break/>For his hands refuse to labour.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>There is that coveteth greedily all the day long;  <paragraph-break/>But the righteous giveth and spareth not.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>The sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination;  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>How much more, when he bringeth it with the proceeds of wickedness?  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>A false witness shall perish;  <paragraph-break/>But the man that obeyeth shall speak unchallenged.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>29</verse-number>A wicked man hardeneth his face;  <paragraph-break/>But as for the upright, he looketh well to his way.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>30</verse-number>There is no wisdom nor understanding  <paragraph-break/>Nor counsel against the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>31</verse-number>The horse is prepared against the day of battle;  <paragraph-break/>But victory is of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>22</chapter-number>A good name is rather to be  chosen than great riches,  <paragraph-break/>And loving favour rather than silver and gold.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>The rich and the poor meet together— <paragraph-break/>The <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> is the maker of them all.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>A prudent man seeth the evil, and hideth himself;  <paragraph-break/>But the thoughtless pass on, and are punished.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>The reward of humility is the fear of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>,  <paragraph-break/>Even riches, and honour, and life.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Thorns and snares are in the way of the froward;  <paragraph-break/>He that keepeth his soul holdeth himself far from them.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Train up a child in the way he should go,  <paragraph-break/>And even when he is old, he will not depart from it.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>The rich ruleth over the poor,  <paragraph-break/>And the borrower is servant to the lender.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>He that soweth iniquity shall reap vanity;  <paragraph-break/>And the rod of his wrath shall fail.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>He that hath a bountiful eye shall be blessed;  <paragraph-break/>For he giveth of his bread to the poor.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>Cast out the scorner, and contention will go out;  <paragraph-break/>Yea, strife and shame will cease.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>He that loveth pureness of heart,  <paragraph-break/>That hath grace in his lips, the king shall be his friend.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>The eyes of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> preserve him that hath knowledge,  <paragraph-break/>But He overthroweth the words of the faithless man.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>The sluggard saith: ‘There is a lion without;  <paragraph-break/>I shall be slain in the streets.’  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>The mouth of strange women is a deep pit:  <paragraph-break/>He that is abhorred of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> shall fall therein.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>Foolishness is bound up in the heart of a child;  <paragraph-break/>But the rod of correction shall drive it far from him.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>One may oppress the poor, yet will their gain increase;  <paragraph-break/>One may give to the rich, yet will want come.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>Incline thine ear, and hear the words of the wise,  <paragraph-break/>And apply thy heart unto my knowledge.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>For it is a pleasant thing if thou keep them within thee;  <paragraph-break/>Let them be established altogether upon thy lips.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>That thy trust may be in the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>,  <paragraph-break/>I have made them known to thee this day, even to thee.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>Have not I written unto thee excellent things  <paragraph-break/>Of counsels and knowledge;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>That I might make thee know the certainty of the words of truth,  <paragraph-break/>That thou mightest bring back words of truth to them that send thee?  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>Rob not the weak, because he is weak,  <paragraph-break/>Neither crush the poor in the gate;  
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>For the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> will plead their cause,  <paragraph-break/>And despoil of life those that despoil them.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>Make no friendship with a man that is given to anger;  <paragraph-break/>And with a wrathful man thou shalt not go;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>Lest thou learn his ways,  <paragraph-break/>And get a snare to thy soul.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>Be thou not of them that strike hands,  <paragraph-break/>Or of them that are sureties for debts;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>If thou hast not wherewith to pay,  <paragraph-break/>Why should he take away thy bed from under thee?  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>Remove not the ancient landmark,  <paragraph-break/>Which thy fathers have set.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>29</verse-number>Seest thou a man diligent in his business? he shall stand before kings;  <paragraph-break/>He shall not stand before mean men.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>23</chapter-number>When thou sittest to eat with a  ruler,  <paragraph-break/>Consider well him that is before thee;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>And put a knife to thy throat,  <paragraph-break/>If thou be a man given to appetite.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>Be not desirous of his dainties;  <paragraph-break/>Seeing they are deceitful food.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>Weary not thyself to be rich;  <paragraph-break/>Cease from thine own wisdom.  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Wilt thou set thine eyes upon it? it is gone;  <paragraph-break/>For riches certainly make themselves wings,  <paragraph-break/>Like an eagle that flieth toward heaven.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Eat thou not the bread of him that hath an evil eye,  <paragraph-break/>Neither desire thou his dainties;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>For as one that hath reckoned within himself, so is he:  <paragraph-break/>‘Eat and drink’, saith he to thee;  <paragraph-break/>But his heart is not with thee.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>The morsel which thou hast eaten shalt thou vomit up,  <paragraph-break/>And lose thy sweet words.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>Speak not in the ears of a fool;  <paragraph-break/>For he will despise the wisdom of thy words.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>Remove not the ancient landmark;  <paragraph-break/>And enter not into the fields of the fatherless;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>For their Redeemer is strong;  <paragraph-break/>He will plead their cause with thee.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>Apply thy heart unto instruction,  <paragraph-break/>And thine ears to the words of knowledge.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>Withhold not correction from the child;  <paragraph-break/>For though thou beat him with the rod, he will not die.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>Thou beatest him with the rod,  <paragraph-break/>And wilt deliver his soul from the nether-world.  
         <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>My son, if thy heart be wise,  <paragraph-break/>My heart will be glad, even mine;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>Yea, my reins will rejoice,  <paragraph-break/>When thy lips speak right things.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>Let not thy heart envy sinners,  <paragraph-break/>But be in the fear of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> all the day;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>For surely there is a future;  <paragraph-break/>And thy hope shall not be cut off.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>Hear thou, my son, and be wise,  <paragraph-break/>And guide thy heart in the way.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>Be not among winebibbers;  <paragraph-break/>Among gluttonous eaters of flesh;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>For the drunkard and the glutton shall come to poverty;  <paragraph-break/>And drowsiness shall clothe a man with rags.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>Hearken unto thy father that begot thee,  <paragraph-break/>And despise not thy mother when she is old.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>Buy the truth, and sell it not;  <paragraph-break/>Also wisdom, and instruction, and understanding.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>The father of the righteous will greatly rejoice;  <paragraph-break/>And he that begetteth a wise child will have joy of him.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>Let thy father and thy mother be glad,  <paragraph-break/>And let her that bore thee rejoice.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>My son, give me thy heart,  <paragraph-break/>And let thine eyes observe my ways.  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>For a harlot is a deep ditch;  <paragraph-break/>And an alien woman is a narrow pit.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>She also lieth in wait as a robber,  <paragraph-break/>And increaseth the faithless among men.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>29</verse-number>Who crieth: ‘Woe’? who: ‘Alas’?  <paragraph-break/>Who hath contentions? who hath raving?  <paragraph-break/>Who hath wounds without cause?  <paragraph-break/>Who hath redness of eyes?  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>30</verse-number>They that tarry long at the wine;  <paragraph-break/>They that go to try mixed wine.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>31</verse-number>Look not thou upon the wine when it is red,  <paragraph-break/>When it giveth its colour in the cup,  <paragraph-break/>When it glideth down smoothly;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>32</verse-number>At the last it biteth like a serpent,  <paragraph-break/>And stingeth like a basilisk.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>33</verse-number>Thine eyes shall behold strange things,  <paragraph-break/>And thy heart shall utter confused things.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>34</verse-number>Yea, thou shalt be as he that lieth down in the midst of the sea,  <paragraph-break/>Or as he that lieth upon the top of a mast.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>35</verse-number>‘They have struck me, and I felt it not,  <paragraph-break/>They have beaten me, and I knew it not;  <paragraph-break/>When shall I awake? I will seek it yet again.’  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>24</chapter-number>Be not thou envious of evil  men, <paragraph-break/>Neither desire to be with them.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>For their heart studieth destruction,  <paragraph-break/>And their lips talk of mischief.  
         <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>Through wisdom is a house builded;  <paragraph-break/>And by understanding it is established;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>And by knowledge are the chambers filled  <paragraph-break/>With all precious and pleasant riches.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>A wise man is strong;  <paragraph-break/>Yea, a man of knowledge increaseth strength.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>For with wise advice thou shalt make thy war;  <paragraph-break/>And in the multitude of counsellors there is safety.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>Wisdom is as unattainable to a fool as corals;  <paragraph-break/>He openeth not his mouth in the gate.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>He that deviseth to do evil,  <paragraph-break/>Men shall call him a mischievous person.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>The thought of foolishness is sin;  <paragraph-break/>And the scorner is an abomination to men.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>If thou faint in the day of adversity,  <paragraph-break/>Thy strength is small indeed.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>Deliver them that are drawn unto death;  <paragraph-break/>And those that are ready to be slain wilt thou forbear to rescue?  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>If thou sayest: ‘Behold, we knew not this’,  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>Doth not He that weigheth the hearts consider it?  <paragraph-break/>And He that keepeth thy soul, doth not He know it?  <paragraph-break/>And shall not He render to every man according to his works?  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>My son, eat thou honey, for it is good,  <paragraph-break/>And the honeycomb is sweet to thy taste;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>So know thou wisdom to be unto thy soul;  <paragraph-break/>If thou hast found it, then shall there be a future,  <paragraph-break/>And thy hope shall not be cut off.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>Lie not in wait, O wicked man, against the dwelling of the righteous,  <paragraph-break/>Spoil not his resting-place;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>For a righteous man falleth seven times, and riseth up again,  <paragraph-break/>But the wicked stumble under adversity.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>Rejoice not when thine enemy falleth,  <paragraph-break/>And let not thy heart be glad when he stumbleth;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>Lest the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> see it, and it displease Him,  <paragraph-break/>And He turn away His wrath from him.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>Fret not thyself because of evildoers,  <paragraph-break/>Neither be thou envious at the wicked;  
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>For there will be no future to the evil man,  <paragraph-break/>The lamp of the wicked shall be put out.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>My son, fear thou the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> and the king,  <paragraph-break/>And meddle not with them that are given to change;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>For their calamity shall rise suddenly;  <paragraph-break/>And who knoweth the ruin from them both?  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>These also are sayings of the wise.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>To have respect of persons in judgment is not good.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>He that saith unto the wicked: ‘Thou art righteous’,  <paragraph-break/>Peoples shall curse him, nations shall execrate him;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>But to them that decide justly shall be delight,  <paragraph-break/>And a good blessing shall come upon them.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>He kisseth the lips  <paragraph-break/>That giveth a right answer.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>Prepare thy work without,  <paragraph-break/>And make it fit for thyself in the field;  <paragraph-break/>And afterwards build thy house.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>Be not a witness against thy neighbour without cause;  <paragraph-break/>And deceive not with thy lips.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>29</verse-number>Say not: ‘I will do so to him as he hath done to me;  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>I will render to the man according to his work.’  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>30</verse-number>I went by the field of the slothful,  <paragraph-break/>And by the vineyard of the man void of understanding;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>31</verse-number>And, lo, it was all grown over with thistles,  <paragraph-break/>The face thereof was covered with nettles,  <paragraph-break/>And the stone wall thereof was broken down.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>32</verse-number>Then I beheld, and considered well;  <paragraph-break/>I saw, and received instruction.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>33</verse-number>‘Yet a little sleep, a little slumber,  <paragraph-break/>A little folding of the hands to sleep’—<paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>34</verse-number>So shall thy poverty come as a runner,  <paragraph-break/>And thy want as an armed man.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>25</chapter-number>These also are proverbs of Solomon, which the men of Hezekiah king of Judah copied out.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>It is the glory of God to conceal a thing; but the glory of kings is to search out a matter.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>The heaven for height, and the earth for depth, and the heart of kings is unsearchable.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>Take away the dross from the silver, and there cometh forth a vessel for the refiner;  
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Take away the wicked from before the king, and his throne shall be established in righteousness.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Glorify not thyself in the presence of the king, and stand not in the place of great men;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>For better is it that it be said unto thee: ‘Come up hither’, than that thou shouldest be put lower in the presence of the prince, whom thine eyes have seen.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>Go not forth hastily to strive, lest thou know not what to do in the end thereof, when thy neighbour hath put thee to shame.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>Debate thy cause with thy neighbour, but reveal not the secret of another;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>Lest he that heareth it revile thee, and thine infamy turn not away.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>A word fitly spoken  <paragraph-break/>Is like apples of gold in settings of silver.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>As an ear-ring of gold, and an ornament of fine gold,  <paragraph-break/>So is a wise reprover upon an obedient ear.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>As the cold of snow in the time of harvest,  <paragraph-break/>So is a faithful messenger to him that sendeth him;  <paragraph-break/>For he refresheth the soul of his master.  <paragraph-break/> 
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>As vapours and wind without rain,  <paragraph-break/>So is he that boasteth himself of a false gift.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>By long forbearing is a ruler persuaded,  <paragraph-break/>And a soft tongue breaketh the bone.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>Hast thou found honey? eat so much as is sufficient for thee,  <paragraph-break/>Lest thou be filled therewith, and vomit it.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>Let thy foot be seldom in thy neighbour’s house;  <paragraph-break/>Lest he be sated with thee, and hate thee.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>As a maul, and a sword, and a sharp arrow,  <paragraph-break/>So is a man that beareth false witness against his neighbour.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>Confidence in an unfaithful man in time of trouble  <paragraph-break/>Is like a broken tooth, and a foot out of joint.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>As one that taketh off a garment in cold weather, and as vinegar upon nitre,  <paragraph-break/>So is he that singeth songs to a heavy heart.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>If thine enemy be hungry, give him bread to eat,  <paragraph-break/>And if he be thirsty, give him water to drink;  
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>For thou wilt heap coals of fire upon his head,  <paragraph-break/>And the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> will reward thee.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>The north wind bringeth forth rain,  <paragraph-break/>And a backbiting tongue an angry countenance.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>It is better to dwell in a corner of the housetop,  <paragraph-break/>Than in a house in common with a contentious woman.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>As cold waters to a faint soul,  <paragraph-break/>So is good news from a far country.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>As a troubled fountain, and a corrupted spring,  <paragraph-break/>So is a righteous man that giveth way before the wicked.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>It is not good to eat much honey;  <paragraph-break/>So for men to search out their own glory is not glory.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>Like a city broken down and without a wall,  <paragraph-break/>So is he whose spirit is without restraint.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>26</chapter-number>As snow in summer, and as  rain in harvest,  <paragraph-break/>So honour is not seemly for a fool.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>As the wandering sparrow, as the flying swallow,  <paragraph-break/>So the curse that is causeless shall come home.  <paragraph-break/>
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>A whip for the horse, a bridle for the ass,  <paragraph-break/>And a rod for the back of fools.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>Answer not a fool according to his folly,  <paragraph-break/>Lest thou also be like unto him.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Answer a fool according to his folly,  <paragraph-break/>Lest he be wise in his own eyes.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>He that sendeth a message by the hand of a fool  <paragraph-break/>Cutteth off his own feet, and drinketh damage.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>The legs hang limp from the lame;  <paragraph-break/>So is a parable in the mouth of fools.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>As a small stone in a heap of stones,  <paragraph-break/>So is he that giveth honour to a fool.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>As a thorn that cometh into the hand of a drunkard,  <paragraph-break/>So is a parable in the mouth of fools.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>A master performeth all things;  <paragraph-break/>But he that stoppeth a fool is as one that stoppeth a flood.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>As a dog that returneth to his vomit,  <paragraph-break/>So is a fool that repeateth his folly.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>Seest thou a man wise in his own eyes?  <paragraph-break/>There is more hope of a fool than of him.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>The sluggard saith: ‘There is a lion in the way;  <paragraph-break/>Yea, a lion is in the streets.’  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>The door is turning upon its hinges,  <paragraph-break/>And the sluggard is still upon his bed.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>The sluggard burieth his hand in the dish;  <paragraph-break/>It wearieth him to bring it back to his mouth.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>The sluggard is wiser in his own eyes  <paragraph-break/>Than seven men that give wise answer.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>He that passeth by, and meddleth with strife not his own,  <paragraph-break/>Is like one that taketh a dog by the ears.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>As a madman who casteth firebrands,  <paragraph-break/>Arrows, and death;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>So is the man that deceiveth his neighbour,  <paragraph-break/>And saith: ‘Am not I in sport?’  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>Where no wood is, the fire goeth out;  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>And where there is no whisperer, contention ceaseth.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>As coals are to burning coals, and wood to fire;  <paragraph-break/>So is a contentious man to kindle strife.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>The words of a whisperer are as dainty morsels,  <paragraph-break/>And they go down into the innermost parts of the body.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>Burning lips and a wicked heart  <paragraph-break/>Are like an earthen vessel overlaid with silver dross.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>He that hateth dissembleth with his lips,  <paragraph-break/>But he layeth up deceit within him.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>When he speaketh fair,  <paragraph-break/>Believe him not;  <paragraph-break/>For there are seven abominations in his heart.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>Though his hatred be concealed with deceit,  <paragraph-break/>His wickedness shall be revealed before the congregation.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>Whoso diggeth a pit shall fall therein;  <paragraph-break/>And he that rolleth a stone, it shall return upon him.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>A lying tongue hateth those that are crushed by it;  <paragraph-break/>And a flattering mouth worketh ruin.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>27</chapter-number>Boast not thyself of to- morrow;  <paragraph-break/>For thou knowest not what a day may bring forth.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>Let another man praise thee, and not thine own mouth;  <paragraph-break/>A stranger, and not thine own lips.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>A stone is heavy, and the sand weighty;  <paragraph-break/>But a fool’s vexation is heavier than they both.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>Wrath is cruel, and anger is overwhelming;  <paragraph-break/>But who is able to stand before jealousy?  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Better is open rebuke  <paragraph-break/>Than love that is hidden.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Faithful are the wounds of a friend;  <paragraph-break/>But the kisses of an enemy are importunate.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>The full soul loatheth a honeycomb;  <paragraph-break/>But to the hungry soul every bitter thing is sweet.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>As a bird that wandereth from her nest,  <paragraph-break/>So is a man that wandereth from his place.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>Ointment and perfume rejoice the heart;  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>So doth the sweetness of a man’s friend by hearty counsel.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>Thine own friend, and thy father’s friend, forsake not;  <paragraph-break/>Neither go into thy brother’s house in the day of thy calamity;  <paragraph-break/>Better is a neighbour that is near than a brother far off.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>My son, be wise, and make my heart glad,  <paragraph-break/>That I may answer him that taunteth me.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>A prudent man seeth the evil, and hideth himself;  <paragraph-break/>But the thoughtless pass on, and are punished.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>Take his garment that is surety for a stranger;  <paragraph-break/>And hold him in pledge that is surety for an alien woman.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>He that blesseth his friend with a loud voice, rising early in the morning,  <paragraph-break/>It shall be counted a curse to him.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>A continual dropping in a very rainy day  <paragraph-break/>And a contentious woman are alike;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>He that would hide her hideth the wind,  <paragraph-break/>And the ointment of his right hand betrayeth itself.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>Iron sharpeneth iron;  
         <paragraph-break/>So a man sharpeneth the countenance of his friend.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>Whoso keepeth the fig-tree shall eat the fruit thereof;  <paragraph-break/>And he that waiteth on his master shall be honoured.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>As in water face answereth to face,  <paragraph-break/>So the heart of man to man.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>The nether-world and Destruction are never satiated;  <paragraph-break/>So the eyes of man are never satiated.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>The refining pot is for silver, and the furnace for gold,  <paragraph-break/>And a man is tried by his praise.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>Though thou shouldest bray a fool in a mortar with a pestle among groats,  <paragraph-break/>Yet will not his foolishness depart from him.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>Be thou diligent to know the state of thy flocks,  <paragraph-break/>And look well to thy herds;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>For riches are not for ever;  <paragraph-break/>And doth the crown endure unto all generations?  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>When the hay is mown, and the tender grass showeth itself,  <paragraph-break/>And the herbs of the mountains are gathered in;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>The lambs will be for thy clothing,  <paragraph-break/>And the goats the price for a field.  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>And there will be goats’milk enough for thy food, for the food of thy household;  <paragraph-break/>And maintenance for thy maidens.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>28</chapter-number>The wicked flee when no man  pursueth;  <paragraph-break/>But the righteous are secure as a young lion.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>For the transgression of a land many are the princes thereof;  <paragraph-break/>But by a man of understanding and knowledge established order shall long continue.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>A poor man that oppresseth the weak  <paragraph-break/>Is like a sweeping rain which leaveth no food.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>They that forsake the law praise the wicked;  <paragraph-break/>But such as keep the law contend with them.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Evil men understand not justice;  <paragraph-break/>But they that seek the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> understand all things.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Better is the poor that walketh in his integrity,  <paragraph-break/>Than he that is perverse in his ways, though he be rich.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>A wise son observeth the teaching; ut he that is a companion of gluttonous men shameth his father.  
         <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>He that augmenteth his substance by interest and increase,  <paragraph-break/>Gathereth it for him that is gracious to the poor.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>He that turneth away his ear from hearing the law,  <paragraph-break/>Even his prayer is an abomination.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>Whoso causeth the upright to go astray in an evil way,  <paragraph-break/>He shall fall himself into his own pit;  <paragraph-break/>But the whole-hearted shall inherit good.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>The rich man is wise in his own eyes;  <paragraph-break/>But the poor that hath understanding searcheth him through.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>When the righteous exult, there is great glory;  <paragraph-break/>But when the wicked rise, men must be sought for.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>He that covereth his transgressions shall not prosper;  <paragraph-break/>But whoso confesseth and forsaketh them shall obtain mercy.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>Happy is the man that feareth alway;  <paragraph-break/>But he that hardeneth his heart shall fall into evil.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>As a roaring lion, and a ravenous bear;  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>So is a wicked ruler over a poor people.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>The prince that lacketh understanding is also a great oppressor;  <paragraph-break/>But he that hateth covetousness shall prolong his days.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>A man that is laden with the blood of any person  <paragraph-break/>Shall hasten his steps unto the pit; none will support him.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>Whoso walketh uprightly shall be saved;  <paragraph-break/>But he that is perverse in his ways shall fall at once.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>He that tilleth his ground shall have plenty of bread;  <paragraph-break/>But he that followeth after vain things shall have poverty enough.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>A faithful man shall abound with blessings;  <paragraph-break/>But he that maketh haste to be rich shall not be unpunished.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>To have respect of persons is not good;  <paragraph-break/>For a man will transgress for a piece of bread.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>He that hath an evil eye hasteneth after riches,  <paragraph-break/>And knoweth not that want shall come upon him.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>He that rebuketh a man shall in the end find more favour  <paragraph-break/>Than he that flattereth with the tongue.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>Whoso robbeth his father or his mother, and saith: ‘It is no transgression’,  <paragraph-break/>The same is the companion of a destroyer.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>He that is of a greedy spirit stirreth up strife;  <paragraph-break/>But he that putteth his trust in the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> shall be abundantly gratified.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>He that trusteth in his own heart is a fool;  <paragraph-break/>But whoso walketh wisely, he shall escape.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>He that giveth unto the poor shall not lack;  <paragraph-break/>But he that hideth his eyes shall have many a curse.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>When the wicked rise, men hide themselves;  <paragraph-break/>But when they perish, the righteous increase.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>29</chapter-number>He that being often reproved  hardeneth his neck  <paragraph-break/>Shall suddenly be broken, and that without remedy.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>When the righteous are increased, the people rejoice;  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>But when the wicked beareth rule, the people sigh.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>Whoso loveth wisdom rejoiceth his father;  <paragraph-break/>But he that keepeth company with harlots wasteth his substance.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>The king by justice establisheth the land;  <paragraph-break/>But he that exacteth gifts overthroweth it.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>A man that flattereth his neighbour  <paragraph-break/>Spreadeth a net for his steps.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>In the transgression of an evil man there is a snare;  <paragraph-break/>But the righteous doth sing and rejoice.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>The righteous taketh knowledge of the cause of the poor;  <paragraph-break/>The wicked understandeth not knowledge.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>Scornful men set a city in a blaze;  <paragraph-break/>But wise men turn away wrath.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>If a wise man contendeth with a foolish man,  <paragraph-break/>Whether he be angry or laugh, there will be no rest.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>The men of blood hate him that is sincere;  <paragraph-break/>And as for the upright, they seek his life.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>A fool spendeth all his spirit;  <paragraph-break/>But a wise man stilleth it within him.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>If a ruler hearkeneth to falsehood,  <paragraph-break/>All his servants are wicked.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>The poor man and the oppressor meet together;  <paragraph-break/>The <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> giveth light to the eyes of them both.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>The king that faithfully judgeth the poor,  <paragraph-break/>His throne shall be established for ever.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>The rod and reproof give wisdom;  <paragraph-break/>But a child left to himself causeth shame to his mother.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>When the wicked are increased, transgression increaseth;  <paragraph-break/>But the righteous shall gaze upon their fall.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>Correct thy son, and he will give thee rest;  <paragraph-break/>Yea, he will give delight unto thy soul.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>Where there is no vision, the people cast off restraint;  <paragraph-break/>But he that keepeth the law, happy is he.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>A servant will not be corrected by words;  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>For though he understand, there will be no response.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>Seest thou a man that is hasty in his words?  <paragraph-break/>There is more hope for a fool than for him.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>He that delicately bringeth up his servant from a child  <paragraph-break/>Shall have him become master at the last.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>An angry man stirreth up strife,  <paragraph-break/>And a wrathful man aboundeth in transgression.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>A man’s pride shall bring him low;  <paragraph-break/>But he that is of a lowly spirit shall attain to honour.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>Whoso is partner with a thief hateth his own soul:  <paragraph-break/>He heareth the adjuration and uttereth nothing.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>The fear of man bringeth a snare;  <paragraph-break/>But whoso putteth his trust in the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps> shall be set up on high.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>Many seek the ruler’s favour;  <paragraph-break/>But a man’s judgment cometh from the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>An unjust man is an abomination to the righteous;  <paragraph-break/>And he that is upright in the way is an abomination to the wicked.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>30</chapter-number>The words of Agur the son of Jakeh; the burden.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>The man saith unto Ithiel, unto Ithiel and Ucal:  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>Surely I am brutish, unlike a man,  <paragraph-break/>And have not the understanding of a man;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>And I have not learned wisdom,  <paragraph-break/>That I should have the knowledge of the Holy One.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>Who hath ascended up into heaven, and descended?  <paragraph-break/>Who hath gathered the wind in his fists?  <paragraph-break/>Who hath bound the waters in his garment?  <paragraph-break/>Who hath established all the ends of the earth?  <paragraph-break/>What is his name, and what is his son’s name, if thou knowest?  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Every word of God is tried;  <paragraph-break/>He is a shield unto them that take refuge in Him.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Add thou not unto His words,  <paragraph-break/>Lest He reprove thee, and thou be found a liar.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>Two things have I asked of Thee;  <paragraph-break/>Deny me them not before I die:  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>Remove far from me falsehood and lies;  <paragraph-break/>Give me neither poverty nor riches; feed me with mine allotted bread;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>Lest I be full, and deny, and say: ‘Who is the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>?’  <paragraph-break/>Or lest I be poor, and steal,  <paragraph-break/>And profane the name of my God.  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>Slander not a servant unto his master,  <paragraph-break/>Lest he curse thee, and thou be found guilty.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>There is a generation that curse their father,  <paragraph-break/>And do not bless their mother.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>There is a generation that are pure in their own eyes,  <paragraph-break/>And yet are not washed from their filthiness.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>There is a generation, Oh how lofty are their eyes!  <paragraph-break/>And their eyelids are lifted up.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>There is a generation whose teeth are as swords, and their great teeth as knives,  <paragraph-break/>To devour the poor from off the earth, and the needy from among men.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>The horseleech hath two daughters: ‘Give, give.’  <paragraph-break/>There are three things that are never satisfied,  <paragraph-break/>Yea, four that say not: ‘Enough’:  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>The grave; and the barren womb;  <paragraph-break/>The earth that is not satisfied with water;  <paragraph-break/>And the fire that saith not: ‘Enough.’  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>The eye that mocketh at his father,  <paragraph-break/>And despiseth to obey his mother,  <paragraph-break/>The ravens of the valley shall pick it out,  <paragraph-break/>And the young vultures shall eat it.  
         <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>There are three things which are too wonderful for me,  <paragraph-break/>Yea, four which I know not:  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>The way of an eagle in the air;  <paragraph-break/>The way of a serpent upon a rock;  <paragraph-break/>The way of a ship in the midst of the sea;  <paragraph-break/>And the way of a man with a young woman.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>So is the way of an adulterous woman;  <paragraph-break/>She eateth, and wipeth her mouth,  <paragraph-break/>And saith: ‘I have done no wickedness.’  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>For three things the earth doth quake,  <paragraph-break/>And for four it cannot endure:  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>For a servant when he reigneth;  <paragraph-break/>And a churl when he is filled with food;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>For an odious woman when she is married;  <paragraph-break/>And a handmaid that is heir to her mistress.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>There are four things which are little upon the earth,  <paragraph-break/>But they are exceeding wise:  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>The ants are a people not strong,  <paragraph-break/>Yet they provide their food in the summer;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>The rock-badgers are but a feeble folk,  <paragraph-break/>Yet make they their houses in the crags;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>The locusts have no king,  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>Yet go they forth all of them by bands;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>The spider thou canst take with the hands,  <paragraph-break/>Yet is she in kings’palaces.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>29</verse-number>There are three things which are stately in their march,  <paragraph-break/>Yea, four which are stately in going:  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>30</verse-number>The lion, which is mightiest among beasts,  <paragraph-break/>And turneth not away for any;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>31</verse-number>The greyhound; the he-goat also;  <paragraph-break/>And the king, against whom there is no rising up.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>32</verse-number>If thou hast done foolishly in lifting up thyself,  <paragraph-break/>Or if thou hast planned devices, lay thy hand upon thy mouth.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>33</verse-number>For the churning of milk bringeth forth curd,  <paragraph-break/>And the wringing of the nose bringeth forth blood;  <paragraph-break/>So the forcing of wrath bringeth forth strife.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>31</chapter-number>The words of king Lemuel; the burden wherewith his mother corrected him.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>What, my son? and what, O son of my womb?  <paragraph-break/>And what, O son of my vows?  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>Give not thy strength unto women,  <paragraph-break/>Nor thy ways to that which destroyeth kings.  
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>It is not for kings, O <note mark="a" id="note-1113-a"> Heb. Lemoel. </note>Lemuel, it is not for kings to drink wine:  <paragraph-break/>Nor for princes to say: ‘Where is strong drink?’  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Lest they drink, and forget that which is decreed,  <paragraph-break/>And pervert the justice due to any that is afflicted.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Give strong drink unto him that is ready to perish,  <paragraph-break/>And wine unto the bitter in soul;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>Let him drink, and forget his poverty,  <paragraph-break/>And remember his misery no more.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>Open thy mouth for the dumb,  <paragraph-break/>In the cause of all such as are appointed to destruction.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>Open thy mouth, judge righteously,  <paragraph-break/>And plead the cause of the poor and needy.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <parashah-title>א</parashah-title>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>A woman of valour who can find?   <paragraph-break/>For her price is far above rubies.  <parashah-title>ב</parashah-title>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>The heart of her husband doth  aafely trust in her,   <paragraph-break/>And he hath no  lack of gain.  <parashah-title>ג</parashah-title> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>She doeth him good and not evil   <paragraph-break/>All the days of her life.  <parashah-title>ד</parashah-title> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>She seeketh wool and flax,   <paragraph-break/>And worketh willingly with her  hands.  <parashah-title>ה</parashah-title> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>She is like the merchant-ships; She bringeth her food from afar.  <parashah-title>ו</parashah-title> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>She riseth also while it is yet  night,  
         
         
            
         
          <paragraph-break/>And giveth food to her household, And a portion to her maidens.  <parashah-title>ז</parashah-title> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>She considereth a field, and  buyeth it;   <paragraph-break/>With the fruit of her hands she  planteth a vineyard.  <parashah-title>ח</parashah-title> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>She girdeth her loins with  strength,   <paragraph-break/>And maketh strong her arms.  <parashah-title>ט</parashah-title> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>18</verse-number>She perceiveth that her  merchandise is good;   <paragraph-break/>Her lamp goeth not out by night.  <parashah-title>י</parashah-title> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>19</verse-number>She layeth her hands to the  distaff,   <paragraph-break/>And her hands hold the spindle.  <parashah-title>כ</parashah-title> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>20</verse-number>She stretcheth out her hand to the  poor;   <paragraph-break/>Yea, she reacheth forth her hands  to the needy.  <parashah-title>ל</parashah-title> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>21</verse-number>She is not afraid of the snow for  her household;   <paragraph-break/>For all her household are clothed  with scarlet.  <parashah-title>מ</parashah-title> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>22</verse-number>She maketh for herself coverlets;   <paragraph-break/>Her clothing is fine linen and  purple.  <parashah-title>נ</parashah-title> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>23</verse-number>Her husband is known in the  gates,   <paragraph-break/>When he sitteth among the elders  of  the land.  
         <parashah-title>ס</parashah-title> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>24</verse-number>She maketh linen garments and  selleth them;   <paragraph-break/>And delivereth girdles unto the  merchant.  <parashah-title>ע</parashah-title> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>25</verse-number>Strength and dignity are her  clothing;   <paragraph-break/>And she laugheth at the time to  come.  <parashah-title>פ</parashah-title> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>26</verse-number>She openeth her mouth with  wisdom;   <paragraph-break/>And the law of kindness is on her  tongue.  <parashah-title>צ</parashah-title> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>27</verse-number>She looketh well to the ways of  her household,   <paragraph-break/>And eateth not the bread of  idleness.  <parashah-title>ק</parashah-title> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>28</verse-number>Her children rise up, and call her  blessed;   <paragraph-break/>Her husband also, and he praiseth  her:  <parashah-title>ר</parashah-title> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>29</verse-number>‘Many daughters have done  valiantly,   <paragraph-break/>But thou excellest them all.’  <parashah-title>ש</parashah-title> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>30</verse-number>Grace is deceitful, and beauty is  vain;   <paragraph-break/>But a woman that feareth the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>,  she shall be praised.  <parashah-title>ת</parashah-title> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>31</verse-number>Give her of the fruit of her hands;   <paragraph-break/>And let her works praise her in the  gates. 
         
      </book>
   </section>
</bible>