<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bible>
   <section id="THE WRITINGS">
      <book id="SONG OF SONGS">
         
            
            <hebrew-title>שיר השירים</hebrew-title>
            <book-title>SONG OF SONGS</book-title>
            
            <paragraph-break/>
            
         
         <chapter-number>1</chapter-number>
         <small-caps>The</small-caps> song of songs, which is Solomon’s.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>Let him kiss me with the kisses of his mouth— <paragraph-break/>For thy love is better than wine.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>Thine ointments have a goodly fragrance;  <paragraph-break/>Thy name is as ointment poured forth;  <paragraph-break/>Therefore do the maidens love thee.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>Draw me, we will run after thee;  <paragraph-break/>The king hath brought me into his chambers;  <paragraph-break/>We will be glad and rejoice in thee,  <paragraph-break/>We will find thy love more fragrant than wine!  <paragraph-break/>Sincerely do they love thee.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>‘I am black, but comely,  <paragraph-break/>O ye daughters of Jerusalem,  <paragraph-break/>As the tents of Kedar,  <paragraph-break/>As the curtains of Solomon.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Look not upon me, that I am swarthy,  <paragraph-break/>That the sun hath tanned me;  <paragraph-break/>My mother’s sons were incensed against me,  <paragraph-break/>They made me keeper of the vineyards;  <paragraph-break/>But mine own vineyard have I not kept.’  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>Tell me, O thou whom my soul loveth,  
         <paragraph-break/>Where thou feedest, where thou makest thy flock to rest at noon;  <paragraph-break/>For why should I be as one that veileth herself  <paragraph-break/>Beside the flocks of thy companions?  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>If thou know not, O thou fairest among women,  <paragraph-break/>Go thy way forth by the footsteps of the flock  <paragraph-break/>And feed thy kids, beside the shepherds’tents.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>I have compared thee, O my love,  <paragraph-break/>To a steed in Pharaoh’s chariots.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>Thy cheeks are comely with circlets,  <paragraph-break/>Thy neck with beads.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>We will make thee circlets of gold  <paragraph-break/>With studs of silver.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>While the king sat at his table,  <paragraph-break/>My spikenard sent forth its fragrance.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>My beloved is unto me as a bag of myrrh,  <paragraph-break/>That lieth betwixt my breasts.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>My beloved is unto me as a cluster of henna  <paragraph-break/>In the vineyards of En-gedi.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>Behold, thou art fair, my love; behold, thou art fair;  <paragraph-break/>Thine eyes are as doves.  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>Behold, thou art fair, my beloved, yea, pleasant;  <paragraph-break/>Also our couch is leafy.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>The beams of our houses are cedars,  <paragraph-break/>And our panels are cypresses.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>2</chapter-number>I am a rose of Sharon,  A lily of the valleys.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>As a lily among thorns,  <paragraph-break/>So is my love among the daughters.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>As an apple-tree among the trees of the wood,  <paragraph-break/>So is my beloved among the sons.  <paragraph-break/>Under its shadow I delighted to sit,  <paragraph-break/>And its fruit was sweet to my taste.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>He hath brought me to the banqueting-house,  <paragraph-break/>And his banner over me is love.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>‘Stay ye me with dainties, refresh me with apples;  <paragraph-break/>For I am love-sick.’  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Let his left hand be under my head,  <paragraph-break/>And his right hand embrace me.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>‘I adjure you, O daughters of Jerusalem,  <paragraph-break/>By the gazelles, and by the hinds of the field,  <paragraph-break/>That ye awaken not, nor stir up love, until it please.’  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>Hark! my beloved! behold, he cometh,  <paragraph-break/>Leaping upon the mountains, skipping upon the hills.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>My beloved is like a gazelle or a young hart;  <paragraph-break/>Behold, he standeth behind our wall,  <paragraph-break/>He looketh in through the windows,  
         <paragraph-break/>He peereth through the lattice.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>My beloved spoke, and said unto me:  <paragraph-break/>‘Rise up, my love, my fair one, and come away.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>For, lo, the winter is past,  <paragraph-break/>The rain is over and gone;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>The flowers appear on the earth;  <paragraph-break/>The time of singing is come,  <paragraph-break/>And the voice of the turtle is heard in our land;  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>The fig-tree putteth forth her green figs,  <paragraph-break/>And the vines in blossom give forth their fragrance.  <paragraph-break/>Arise, my love, my fair one, and come away.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>O my dove, that art in the clefts of the rock, in the covert of the cliff,  <paragraph-break/>Let me see thy countenance, let me hear thy voice;  <paragraph-break/>For sweet is thy voice, and thy countenance is comely.’  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>‘Take us the foxes, the little foxes, that spoil the vineyards;  <paragraph-break/>For our vineyards are in blossom.’  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>My beloved is mine, and I am his,  <paragraph-break/>That feedeth among the lilies.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>17</verse-number>Until the day breathe, and the shadows flee away,  <paragraph-break/>Turn, my beloved, and be thou like a gazelle or a young hart  <paragraph-break/>Upon the mountains of spices.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>3</chapter-number>By night on my bed I sought him  whom my soul loveth;  <paragraph-break/>I sought him, but I found him not.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>‘I will rise now, and go about the city,  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>In the streets and in the broad ways,  <paragraph-break/>I will seek him whom my soul loveth.’  <paragraph-break/>I sought him, but I found him not.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>The watchmen that go about the city found me:  <paragraph-break/>‘Saw ye him whom my soul loveth?’  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>Scarce had I passed from them,  <paragraph-break/>When I found him whom my soul loveth:  <paragraph-break/>I held him, and would not let him go,  <paragraph-break/>Until I had brought him into my mother’s house,  <paragraph-break/>And into the chamber of her that conceived me.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>‘I adjure you, O daughters of Jerusalem,  <paragraph-break/>By the gazelles, and by the hinds of the field,  <paragraph-break/>That ye awaken not, nor stir up love,  <paragraph-break/>Until it please.’  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Who is this that cometh up out of the wilderness  <paragraph-break/>Like pillars of smoke,  <paragraph-break/>Perfumed with myrrh and frankincense,  <paragraph-break/>With all powders of the merchant?  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>Behold, it is the litter of Solomon;  <paragraph-break/>Threescore mighty men are about it,  <paragraph-break/>Of the mighty men of Israel.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>They all handle the sword,  <paragraph-break/>And are expert in war;  <paragraph-break/>Every man hath his sword upon his thigh,  <paragraph-break/>Because of dread in the night.  
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>King Solomon made himself a palanquin  <paragraph-break/>Of the wood of Lebanon.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>He made the pillars thereof of silver,  <paragraph-break/>The top thereof of gold,  <paragraph-break/>The seat of it of purple,  <paragraph-break/>The inside thereof being inlaid with love,  <paragraph-break/>From the daughters of Jerusalem.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>Go forth, O ye daughters of Zion,  <paragraph-break/>And gaze upon king Solomon,  <paragraph-break/>Even upon the crown wherewith his mother hath crowned him in the day of his espousals,  <paragraph-break/>And in the day of the gladness of his heart.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>4</chapter-number>Behold, thou art fair, my love;  behold, thou art fair;  <paragraph-break/>Thine eyes are as doves behind thy veil;  <paragraph-break/>Thy hair is as a flock of goats, that trail down from mount Gilead.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>Thy teeth are like a flock of ewes all shaped alike,  <paragraph-break/>Which are come up from the washing;  <paragraph-break/>Whereof all are paired, and none faileth among them.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>Thy lips are like a thread of scarlet,  <paragraph-break/>And thy mouth is comely;  <paragraph-break/>Thy temples are like a pomegranate split open  <paragraph-break/>Behind thy veil.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>Thy neck is like the tower of David  <paragraph-break/>Builded with turrets,  <paragraph-break/>Whereon there hang a thousand shields,  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>All the armour of the mighty men.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Thy two breasts are like two fawns  <paragraph-break/>That are twins of a gazelle,  <paragraph-break/>Which feed among the lilies.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Until the day breathe,  <paragraph-break/>And the shadows flee away,  <paragraph-break/>I will get me to the mountain of myrrh,  <paragraph-break/>And to the hill of frankincense.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>Thou art all fair, my love;  <paragraph-break/>And there is no spot in thee.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>Come with me from Lebanon, my bride,  <paragraph-break/>With me from Lebanon;  <paragraph-break/>Look from the top of Amana,  <paragraph-break/>From the top of Senir and Hermon,  <paragraph-break/>From the lions’dens,  <paragraph-break/>From the mountains of the leopards.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>Thou hast ravished my heart, my sister, my bride;  <paragraph-break/>Thou hast ravished my heart with one of thine eyes,  <paragraph-break/>With one bead of thy necklace.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>How fair is thy love, my sister, my bride!  <paragraph-break/>How much better is thy love than wine!  <paragraph-break/>And the smell of thine ointments than all manner of spices!  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>Thy lips, O my bride, drop honey— <paragraph-break/>Honey and milk are under thy tongue;  <paragraph-break/>And the smell of thy garments is like the smell of Lebanon.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>A garden shut up is my sister, my bride;  <paragraph-break/>A spring shut up, a fountain sealed.  
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>Thy shoots are a park of pomegranates,  <paragraph-break/>With precious fruits;  <paragraph-break/>Henna with spikenard plants,  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>Spikenard and saffron, calamus and cinnamon,  <paragraph-break/>With all trees of frankincense;  <paragraph-break/>Myrrh and aloes, with all the chief spices.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>Thou art a fountain of gardens,  <paragraph-break/>A well of living waters,  <paragraph-break/>And flowing streams from Lebanon.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>Awake, O north wind;  <paragraph-break/>And come, thou south;  <paragraph-break/>Blow upon my garden,  <paragraph-break/>That the spices thereof may flow out.  <paragraph-break/>Let my beloved come into his garden,  <paragraph-break/>And eat his precious fruits.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>5</chapter-number>I am come into my garden, my  sister, my bride;  <paragraph-break/>I have gathered my myrrh with my spice;  <paragraph-break/>I have eaten my honeycomb with my honey;  <paragraph-break/>I have drunk my wine with my milk.  <paragraph-break/>Eat, O friends;  <paragraph-break/>Drink, yea, drink abundantly, O beloved.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>I sleep, but my heart waketh;  <paragraph-break/>Hark! my beloved knocketh:  <paragraph-break/>‘Open to me, my sister, my love, my dove, my undefiled;  <paragraph-break/>For my head is filled with dew,  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>My locks with the drops of the night.’  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>I have put off my coat;  <paragraph-break/>How shall I put it on?  <paragraph-break/>I have washed my feet;  <paragraph-break/>How shall I defile them?  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>My beloved put in his hand by the hole of the door,  <paragraph-break/>And my heart was moved for him.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>I rose up to open to my beloved;  <paragraph-break/>And my hands dropped with myrrh,  <paragraph-break/>And my fingers with flowing myrrh,  <paragraph-break/>Upon the handles of the bar.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>I opened to my beloved;  <paragraph-break/>But my beloved had turned away, and was gone.  <paragraph-break/>My soul failed me when he spoke.  <paragraph-break/>I sought him, but I could not find him;  <paragraph-break/>I called him, but he gave me no answer.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>The watchmen that go about the city found me,  <paragraph-break/>They smote me, they wounded me;  <paragraph-break/>The keepers of the walls took away my mantle from me.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>‘I adjure you, O daughters of Jerusalem,  <paragraph-break/>If ye find my beloved, what will ye tell him?  <paragraph-break/>That I am love-sick.’  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>‘What is thy beloved more than another beloved,  <paragraph-break/>O thou fairest among women?  <paragraph-break/>What is thy beloved more than another beloved,  <paragraph-break/>That thou dost so adjure us?’  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>‘My beloved is white and ruddy,  <paragraph-break/>Pre-eminent above ten thousand.  
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>His head is as the most fine gold,  <paragraph-break/>His locks are curled,  <paragraph-break/>And black as a raven.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>His eyes are like doves  <paragraph-break/>Beside the water-brooks;  <paragraph-break/>Washed with milk,  <paragraph-break/>And fitly set.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>His cheeks are as a bed of spices,  <paragraph-break/>As banks of sweet herbs;  <paragraph-break/>His lips are as lilies,  <paragraph-break/>Dropping with flowing myrrh.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>His hands are as rods of gold  <paragraph-break/>Set with beryl;  <paragraph-break/>His body is as polished ivory  <paragraph-break/>Overlaid with sapphires.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>15</verse-number>His legs are as pillars of marble,  <paragraph-break/>Set upon sockets of fine gold;  <paragraph-break/>His aspect is like Lebanon,  <paragraph-break/>Excellent as the cedars.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>16</verse-number>His mouth is most sweet;  <paragraph-break/>Yea, he is altogether lovely.  <paragraph-break/>This is my beloved, and this is my friend,  <paragraph-break/>O daughters of Jerusalem.’  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>6</chapter-number>’<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>Whither is thy beloved gone,  O thou fairest among women?  <paragraph-break/>Whither hath thy beloved turned him,  <paragraph-break/>That we may seek him with thee?’  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>‘My beloved is gone down into his garden,  <paragraph-break/>To the beds of spices,  <paragraph-break/>To feed in the gardens,  <paragraph-break/>And to gather lilies.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>I am my beloved’s, and my beloved is mine,  <paragraph-break/>That feedeth among the lilies.’  <paragraph-break/>
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>Thou art beautiful, O my love, as Tirzah,  <paragraph-break/>Comely as Jerusalem,  <paragraph-break/>Terrible as an army with banners.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Turn away thine eyes from me,  <paragraph-break/>For they have overcome me.  <paragraph-break/>Thy hair is as a flock of goats,  <paragraph-break/>That trail down from Gilead.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Thy teeth are like a flock of ewes,  <paragraph-break/>Which are come up from the washing;  <paragraph-break/>Whereof all are paired,  <paragraph-break/>And none faileth among them.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>Thy temples are like a pomegranate split open  <paragraph-break/>Behind thy veil.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>There are threescore queens,  <paragraph-break/>And fourscore concubines,  <paragraph-break/>And maidens without number.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>My dove, my undefiled, is but one;  <paragraph-break/>She is the only one of her mother;  <paragraph-break/>She is the choice one of her that bore her.  <paragraph-break/>The daughters saw her, and called her happy;  <paragraph-break/>Yea, the queens and the concubines, and they praised her.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>Who is she that looketh forth as the dawn,  <paragraph-break/>Fair as the moon,  <paragraph-break/>Clear as the sun,  <paragraph-break/>Terrible as an army with banners?  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>I went down into the garden of nuts,  <paragraph-break/>To look at the green plants of the valley,  <paragraph-break/>To see whether the vine budded,  <paragraph-break/>And the pomegranates were in flower.  
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>Before I was aware, my soul set me  <paragraph-break/>Upon the chariots of my princely people.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>7</chapter-number>Return, return, O Shulammite;  Return, return, that we may look  upon thee.  <paragraph-break/> 
         <paragraph-break/>What will ye see in the Shulammite?  <paragraph-break/>As it were a dance of two companies.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>How beautiful are thy steps in sandals,  <paragraph-break/>O prince’s daughter!  <paragraph-break/>The roundings of thy thighs are like the links of a chain,  <paragraph-break/>The work of the hands of a skilled workman.   <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>Thy navel is like a round goblet,  <paragraph-break/>Wherein no mingled wine is wanting;  <paragraph-break/>Thy belly is like a heap of wheat  <paragraph-break/>Set about with lilies.   <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>Thy two breasts are like two fawns  <paragraph-break/>That are twins of a gazelle.   <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Thy neck is as a tower of ivory;  <paragraph-break/>Thine eyes as the pools in Heshbon,  <paragraph-break/>By the gate of Bath-rabbim;  <paragraph-break/>Thy nose is like the tower of Lebanon  <paragraph-break/>Which looketh toward Damascus.   <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Thy head upon thee is like Carmel,  <paragraph-break/>And the hair of thy head like purple;  <paragraph-break/>The king is held captive in the tresses thereof.   <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>How fair and how pleasant art thou,  <paragraph-break/>O love, for delights!   
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>This thy stature is like to a palm-tree,  <paragraph-break/>And thy breasts to clusters of grapes.   <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>I said: ‘I will climb up into the palm-tree,  <paragraph-break/>I will take hold of the branches thereof;  <paragraph-break/>And let thy breasts be as clusters of the vine,  <paragraph-break/>And the smell of thy countenance like apples;   <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>And the roof of thy mouth like the best wine,  <paragraph-break/>That glideth down smoothly for my beloved,  <paragraph-break/>Moving gently the lips of those that are asleep.’  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>I am my beloved’s,  <paragraph-break/>And his desire is toward me.   <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>Come, my beloved, let us go forth into the field;  <paragraph-break/>Let us lodge in the villages.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>Let us get up early to the vineyards;  <paragraph-break/>Let us see whether the vine hath budded,  <paragraph-break/>Whether the vine-blossom be opened,  <paragraph-break/>And the pomegranates be in flower;  <paragraph-break/>There will I give thee my love.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>The mandrakes give forth fragrance,  <paragraph-break/>And at our doors are all manner of precious fruits,  <paragraph-break/>New and old,  <paragraph-break/>Which I have laid up for thee, O my beloved.  
         <paragraph-break/> 
         <chapter-number>8</chapter-number>Oh that thou wert as my brother,  That sucked the breasts of my  mother!  <paragraph-break/>When I should find thee without, I would kiss thee;  <paragraph-break/>Yea, and none would despise me.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>2</verse-number>I would lead thee, and bring thee into my mother’s house,  <paragraph-break/>That thou mightest instruct me;  <paragraph-break/>I would cause thee to drink of spiced wine,  <paragraph-break/>Of the juice of my pomegranate.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>3</verse-number>His left hand should be under my head,  <paragraph-break/>And his right hand should embrace me.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>4</verse-number>‘I adjure you, O daughters of Jerusalem:  <paragraph-break/>Why should ye awaken, or stir up love,  <paragraph-break/>Until it please?’  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>5</verse-number>Who is this that cometh up from the wilderness,  <paragraph-break/>Leaning upon her beloved?  <paragraph-break/>Under the apple-tree I awakened thee;  <paragraph-break/>There thy mother was in travail with thee;  <paragraph-break/>There was she in travail and brought thee forth.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>6</verse-number>Set me as a seal upon thy heart,  <paragraph-break/>As a seal upon thine arm;  <paragraph-break/>For love is strong as death,  <paragraph-break/>Jealousy is cruel as the grave;  <paragraph-break/>The flashes thereof are flashes of fire,  
         
         
            
         
         <paragraph-break/>A very flame of the <small-caps>Lord</small-caps>.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>7</verse-number>Many waters cannot quench love,  <paragraph-break/>Neither can the floods drown it;  <paragraph-break/>If a man would give all the substance of his house for love,  <paragraph-break/>He would utterly be contemned.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>8</verse-number>We have a little sister,  <paragraph-break/>And she hath no breasts;  <paragraph-break/>What shall we do for our sister  <paragraph-break/>In the day when she shall be spoken for?  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>9</verse-number>If she be a wall,  <paragraph-break/>We will build upon her a turret of silver;  <paragraph-break/>And if she be a door,  <paragraph-break/>We will enclose her with boards of cedar.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>10</verse-number>I am a wall,  <paragraph-break/>And my breasts like the towers thereof;  <paragraph-break/>Then was I in his eyes  <paragraph-break/>As one that found peace.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>11</verse-number>Solomon had a vineyard at Baal-hamon;  <paragraph-break/>He gave over the vineyard unto keepers;  <paragraph-break/>Every one for the fruit thereof  <paragraph-break/>Brought in a thousand pieces of silver.  <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>12</verse-number>My vineyard, which is mine, is before me;  <paragraph-break/>Thou, O Solomon, shalt have the thousand,  <paragraph-break/>And those that keep the fruit thereof two hundred.  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>13</verse-number>Thou that dwellest in the gardens,  <paragraph-break/>The companions hearken for thy voice:  <paragraph-break/>‘Cause me to hear it.’  <paragraph-break/>
         <paragraph-break/>
         <verse-number>14</verse-number>Make haste, my beloved,  <paragraph-break/>And be thou like to a gazelle or to a young hart  <paragraph-break/>Upon the mountains of spices. 
         
      </book>
   </section>
</bible>