<?xml version = "1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="XSL/Tanach.xsl.xml"?>
<!-- Copyright C.V.Kimball 2010 -->
<Tanach>
<!-- The following is a simplified version of the About page. 
     and is intended to be read only by search engines.
     Actual operation is through the XSLT transformation file,
     XSL/Tanach.xsl.xml, specified above. 
-->
<h1>Unicode/XML Leningrad Codex</h1>
The Hebrew bible, the Tanach, has been transcribed from the electronic 
text of the Leningrad Codex maintained by the J. Alan Groves Center for 
Advanced Biblical Research to a modern Unicode and XML-based format. The Coding
page describes the transcription process. The license of use is very generous.
<p/>
Text can be rapidly accessed by providing a citation, i.e. Deut 26:5-9, in a 
text field or by clicking on a succession of links. Text can be displayed in 
a variety of formats and font sizes. Hebrew text may be highlighted, copied, 
and pasted into Unicode compatible applications. Books of the Torah have an 
option to display source markings of the Documentary Hypothesis (DH). 
Files include a standard Text Encoding Initiative header describing the provenance 
of the text..
<p/>
<ul>
<li>The Hebrew text is freely available  with <b>XML</b> markup or without any markup
as text files. The text files are an official repository
of the Groves Center for the Westminster Leningrad Codex in Unicode.</li>
<p/>
<li>An <b>HTML Server</b> is available separately to provide 
<i>standalone</i> Hebrew text in a flexible, user-selected format.</li>
<p/>
<li>An RSS feed of random verses
  provides a learning challenge.</li>
<p/>
<li>Text-dependent links to external sites, such as translations,
 may be created. </li>
<p/>
<li>The software that generated the site is freely
   available as Java source and class files. </li>
</ul>
Notices about the site are published on the <b>b-hebrew</b> mailing list at 
<b><tt>http://lists.ibiblio.org/mailman/listinfo/b-hebrew</tt></b>.  The subject line
of the notices contains the phrase "Unicode/XML Westminster Leningrad Codex".
<p/>
Transcriber: Christopher V. Kimball, West Redding, CT, USA
<p/>
</Tanach>
